<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A quartron of reasons of Catholike religion, with as many briefe reasons of refusall: By Tho. Hill</title>
            <author>Hill, Edmund Thomas, ca. 1563-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 220 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113265</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848502</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848502</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 466:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A quartron of reasons of Catholike religion, with as many briefe reasons of refusall: By Tho. Hill</title>
                  <author>Hill, Edmund Thomas, ca. 1563-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 159, [1], 160-187 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[English Secret Press], with Priuiledge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Antwerpe [i.e. England] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint is false; actual imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Title page has cut of crucifixion--STC.</note>
                  <note>Answered by STC 37 and STC 6889.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13600:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13600:1"/>
            <p>A QVARTRON OF REASONS OF CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKE <hi>RELIGION, WITH AS</hi> MANY BRIEFE REASONS <hi>OF REFVSALL:</hi> By Tho. Hill.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the Crucifixion</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at Antwerpe, with Priuiledge.</hi> 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13600:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13600:2"/>
            <head>A COPPY OF A LETTER SENT FROM TVVO CITIZENS of London, to theyr friend remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning beyond the Seas for cauſe of Religion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E had great hope (deare friend) that you would haue beene a ſtay and comforte to vs all, and an ornament to your kinred and Countrie, and therefore no coſtes nor charges were ſpared in bringing you vp in learning, but all was thought well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, not doubting but if God ſpared you life, you woulde in time be able, not onlie to prouide well for your owne ſelfe, but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:13600:3"/>
to pleaſure the beſt of your friendes. But wee ſee all to fall out quite contrarie, to our great griefe &amp; endleſſe anguiſh: for the blinde opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and ſelfe-willed conceites which you haue taken, haue ouerthrowne the good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune which otherwiſe lay before you, they haue diſcredited you with your kinred, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced you in your countrey, cauſed you to haue your natiue ſoile, and to leade a poore life in a ſtrainge lande. And yet all theſe might in ſome ſort be borne, were they not accompanied with the endleſſe mone of your Parents. If you well remember, you were long ſince told, that if you perſeuered to take, &amp; to holde ſuch opinions as you then began to doe, your burning woulde ſtande you in ſmall ſteede, and conſequently your kinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes and friendes ſhould haue little ioy, or comfort of you. And ſo we ſee it is come to paſſe. Your aged Parentes neuer ceaſe to vrge vs to write to you, to mooue you yet at the length to remember your ſelfe, and either by returning to amende all which is amiſſe, or elſe by ſhewing ſome Reaſons to purge your ſelfe, and ſo to yeelde them ſome ſatisfaction. We therefore praye you in all kindneſſe to write vnto vs, &amp; if by no meanes
<pb facs="tcp:13600:3"/>
you will be drawen backe from this dolefull courſe, yet vouchſafe to ſet down ſome reaſons of your Religion, to the ende you may cleare and purge your ſelfe of the ſuspition of ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe, and ſelfe-wilfulneſſe. For you are mightily condemned, and of your kinsfolkes heere, thought to bee,<note place="margin">Bud. ex Cicer.</note> 
               <hi>Opinator vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens,</hi> one very opinatiue, for that you ſticke ſo ſtifly to the olde, which heere in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of all ſorts is vtterlye condemned as a groſſe and a palpable errour. Yet haue not wee your louing friendes ſo baſe conceit of you, but wee rather thinke that you haue great and weightie Reaſons (at the leaſt in your owne iudgement) to mooue you to take ſo harde a courſe as you doe. Our deſire therefore is, that wee may haue them written, and ſent vs in as briefe manner as you poſsibly maye, (for to returne wee will not mooue you, except we thought you would conforme your ſelfe to the Lawes and Religion of your Countrey) thereby to ſhew and to declare to them who wiſhe you well, that you are no ſuch opinions companion, as ſome woulde haue you to be. Thus hoping you haue a care to accompliſhe our requeſt, and not to reiecte our Letters, and neglecte
<pb facs="tcp:13600:4"/>
the aunſwering of them, as your woonte and cuſtome hath beene heretofore, with our moſt hartie commendations, wee commit you to God Almightie. London this <hi>13.</hi> of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember. <hi>1599.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing friends, R. &amp; G.H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13600:4"/>
            <head>A COPPIE OF THE ANSWERE TO THE LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter afore-going.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y DEERE AND</hi> louing friendes, the <hi>23.</hi> of Octob. Ann. <hi>1599.</hi> I receiued your Letter, dated the <hi>13.</hi> of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember of the ſame yere. In it you giue me to vnderſtand, how that my Parents, with other of my kindred, as alſo you your ſelues do greatly grieue for that you are fruſtrated of the hope, and expectation, you had of my worldly abilitie in time to come, with many other profes, of my blinde opinion, ſelfe-willed conceites, croſsing my good fortune, of diſgrace among my kindred, baniſhement, pouerty, and of other ſuch like. All which wordes I count but as winde, or
<pb facs="tcp:13600:5"/>
as vaine floriſhes, the more for that I ſee all your affection towardes me to be meere car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and that you loue me, <hi>Amore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcentiae,</hi> rather than <hi>Amore amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> ſeeking your owne good thereby, as may appeare by your owne writing, yet doe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter all in the beſt manner. And whatſoeuer you write or ſay, I knowe doth proceede from loue and affection, and from true amity, but yet ſauoring meerly of fleſhe and bloode. I knowe my Parents to be kinde and louing, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as nature giueth to them the inſtinct ſo to be, and I for my part am ready, &amp; euer haue beene to yeelde to them all duty of an obedient Sonne, as alſo to you the offices re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a kinde friende. But this I muſt entreat both them and you, to giue me leaue to ſerue and to honour God Almighty, who is Father of all Fathers, and therefore more to be harkened vnto than any kindred, yea or creature whatſoeuer. Which thing I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe but by cleauing to this Religion, wherein I was Borne, Baptiſed, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and which I am moſt ſtrongly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in my vnderſtanding and conſcience, to be the onely true Religion. Which ſetled perſwaſion and aſſurance of Faith is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooueable
<pb facs="tcp:13600:5"/>
by any humane meanes, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in vaine doe you write ſuch letters vnto me, and in vaine doe my Parentes grieue at my courſe, for I more lament your ſtate and theirs, than you doe mine. Aſſure your ſelfes that I can neuer be perſwaded but that I take the only way to gaine Heauen, and ſo to ſaue my ſoule, and only for that ende doe I take this courſe of life, as God Almighty beſt knoweth, and mee thinketh you ſhould not deeme it to be any diſcredite or diſgrace ſo to doe, conſidering I cleaue to the Religion of all our Aunceſtours and Forefathers, which hath beene Vniuerſall ouer all Chriſtendome, for aboue theſe thowſand yeeres, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot diſgrace me, but it muſt diſgrace the whole Chriſtian worlde alſo. Indeede if I tooke or helde any newe opinions, as of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaniſme, Browniſme, Martiniſme, or of Family of Loue, or ſuch like newe-sprung conceits, you might both iuſtly condemne my courſe, &amp; be vtterly aſhamed of ſuch a brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke fellowe as ſhould croſſe his worldly wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare by ſuch ſottiſhneſſe, and ſelfe-wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. To ſatisfie my Parents and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, I haue heere written and ſent you a Quartron of Reaſons of Religion, not intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:13600:6"/>
thereby to perſwade you or others there, to this religion which I profeſſe, becauſe I know that to be daungerous, as prohibited by the lawes of the land wherein you liue; but onlie to ſhewe to them who wiſhe mee well, what groundes, and reaſons I haue for my doinges. I could haue yeelded you ſo many (if I had thought it fit ſo to haue done) as would haue made vp a iuſt volume, and yet haue left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde me infinite moe: but I thought theſe to ſuffice, for that I know you haue not leaſure, or at the leaſt are vnwilling to trouble your ſelues with reading ouermuch of ſuch matter. I tearme them a quartron of reaſons, becauſe that number is vſuall here in this Countrie, ſignifying the fourth part, or quarter of an hundred; for when they will name any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as we vſually doe when we ſay a dozen, a ſcoare, &amp;c. they ſay vnquartron, and by that number they commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly buy buttons, lace, &amp;c. as we doe by dozens in England. Take them in good part my deare friendes, and aſſure your ſelues that whereſoeuer I liue, I will ſtill carrie a true Engliſh hart with mee, by euer bearing a ſacred &amp; reuerent respect towards my Soueraigne Princeſſe, and my deare coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie; as alſo a dutifull and obedient minde to
<pb facs="tcp:13600:6"/>
my louing Parents, and a friendlie affection towardes you: for I would not haue you to thinke, that liuing out of my Countrie for my conſcience, doth any way hinder the duties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid: for I call God to witneſſe, who is the ſearcher of all hearts, that (my Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) I be are all loyaltie, affection, &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, which a poore Subiect ought to doe, towards our Soueraigne Queene Elizabeth, (whom I pray God bountifully to bleſſe, and allaue affection towardes my natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, with duty to Parents, and loue to kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as is aforeſaid. And thus deſiring my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; mothers bleſsing, with many humble commendations to them, and no fewer to you, I leaue you to our Lord, who ſend vs all of his heauenly grace. From my Chamber at Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempyne this <hi>16.</hi> of Februarie Anno <hi>1600.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very louing friend. T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="reason">
            <pb facs="tcp:13600:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13600:7"/>
            <head>THE I. REASON. If the Prophecies of the Holy Bible be true, (as they be most true) then muſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the Proteſtants needes be falſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EFORE the comming of the MESSIAS, there was not any people, or nation which did ſerue the true and liuing God, but only the Iewes, all others whatſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouerwhelmed in a Sea of blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; worſhipping falſe Gods, which indeede were Diuels, and therevpon the Maiſter Diuell LVCIFER vvas tearmed <hi>Princeps huius mundi:</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Ioan. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Prince of this world,</hi> for that hee was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored and worſhipped in all Lands, &amp; Kingdomes, Iewrie, and that in part,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13600:8"/>
only excepted: which miſerable ſtate &amp; condition God of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie greatlie pittying, promiſed in time to ſend a Sauiour, vvhich ſhould Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme all nations &amp; people, free them from that pittiful ſeruitude and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and bring them to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of true and right Religion, by ſuffering death, and conſequently by planting a Church, to the which al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould repaire. This he did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell by diuerſe &amp; ſundry Prophets, as by <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 2.</note> who ſaide the Church ſhould be as a mountaine, to the which, <hi>All Nations ſhould flowe. And many people ſhall goe and ſay: Come and let vs aſcende to the mountaine of our Lorde:</hi> and after, <hi>Idolles ſhall vtterly be bruſed,</hi> and to be briefe, all this Chapter, yea all the reſt in a manner fore-ſhewe the ſame matter, declaring moſt plainely the conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Nations to the Church of the <hi>Meſsias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 49. &amp; 60. Dan. 2. &amp; 7. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 47. Mich. 4.</note> and how Kings and Queenes ſhould come and doe homage vnto it, &amp; that it ſhould euer continue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interruption, and that it ſhould be moſt ample &amp; large the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13600:8"/>
moſt manifeſtly foretelleth,<note place="margin">Luc. 1. Pſal. 71.</note> ſaying that it ſhould extend, <hi>From Sea to Sea,</hi> and <hi>from the riuer to the endes of the world,</hi> and howe the <hi>Aethiopians</hi> ſhoulde fall downe <hi>Before the Meſsias,</hi> with the kings of <hi>Tharſis, Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Saba,</hi> and to be ſhort, all kings, and people ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this Church, as innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable propeſies of the olde Teſtament doe plainely foreſhewe. Heereupon it was that good men thirſted, &amp; longed ſo greatlye for the comming of the <hi>Meſsias,</hi> knowing that by him all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which ſate in darckeneſſe, and in the ſhadowe of death, ſhould be ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened, deliuered, and ſet in the right way to Heauen. And ſo our Sauiour himſelfe beeing now in the way to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to ſuffer, ſaide. <hi>Nowe the Prince of this world ſhall be caſt out:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.</note> and <hi>If I ſhall be exalted from the earth, I will drawe all to to my ſelfe;</hi> meaning by his Pasſion to drawe al people from heatheniſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry to ſerue him. Nowe if the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Papiſts (as theſe new men tearme them) be falſe and erroneous, then is it againſt the <hi>Meſsias,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13600:9"/>
it is a Religion of the diuels owne inuention, and he the maſter &amp; inſpirer thereof, and ſo by it he is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and worſhiped, and then muſt it needs followe that the Prophets were falſe, yea Chriſt himſelfe ſaid not true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, in telling his Diſciples, <hi>That the Prince</hi> of this worlde, that is, the diuell ſhould then be caſt out, and that hee woulde drawe all to himſelfe, for that ſince his Paſſion, the diuell hath had a more large and ample dominion than he had before. For before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the <hi>Meſsias,</hi> the people of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and almoſt all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Trybes, and Kingdomes, haue beene euer in <hi>Lucifer</hi> his thraldome vntil this our age, in which <hi>Luther</hi> came to expell <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and to ridde all the worlde out of his captiuity. And ſo the Paſſion of our Re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deemer auailed little or nothing at all for the ſpace of theſe fifteene hundred yeres, &amp; for a thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres together he was not ſo far from drawing all vnto him as he ſaide he woulde doe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.</note> that he drewe not ſo much as one perſon, that any man can
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13600:9"/>
name. And in our owne Countrey there of <hi>England,</hi> it is moſt manifeſt that all were Papiſts, without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from the firſt Chriſtening there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vntill this age of King HENRY the eight.<note place="margin">Luther. in poſtil. Ger 1537. part. 2. fol. 141.</note> And ſo the Proteſtantes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme of other Countries, and boldly ſay, that vntil this age, the Goſpel lay in the duſt, and was hidden vnder the benche, &amp; CHRIST was vnknowen. Which to ſay (as the proteſtants muſt needes ſay, &amp; bluſh not ſo to ſay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) is meer madneſſe, &amp; flat infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and a plaine denying of Chriſt, &amp; no ſmall eſtabliſhement of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets religion. For the Proteſtants &amp; Mahometanes agree in this, that the Church which Chriſt founded, fell ſome fiue or ſixe hundred yeeres, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Aſcenſion, into moſt horrible errours, and then (ſay the <hi>Turkes</hi>) the Angell <hi>Gabriell</hi> was ſent from God to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> to teach him how he ſhould reforme the ſaide Church, becauſe it woulde not ſtande with the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and goodneſſe of Almightye God, to ſuffer his Church to vaniſhe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13600:10"/>
away through errous, &amp; ſuperſtitions, without ſending in time to reforme it. And in this out of doubte the <hi>Turkes</hi> haue far greater reaſon than the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes haue, which Proteſtantes by their Doctrine make Chriſt the moſt ſimple, and moſt improuident Lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer that euer was in the world. For neither <hi>Plato, Solon, Lyeurgus,</hi> nor any other Lawe-maker whoſoeuer, was ſo ſimple and improuident, as to faſhion and plant a common wealth, which before it were well ſetled, ſhould va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe away, and come to nothing, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no ſufficient meanes to preuent errours, and ſuch abuſes as would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe their Lawes, and deſtroie their common wealthes. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if Chriſt be God, and the Holie Bible true, the religion of the Papiſts, muſt needes be that religion which he ordayned, and lefte to all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and conſequentlye, the onelie true and right religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="reason">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13600:10"/>
            <head>THE II. REASON. The name of Catholikes.</head>
            <p>NO man can iuſtlie deny, but that they who euer haue holden the name of Catholikes, and haue beene knowne thereby, were vndoubtedlie of true religion, for that they had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer on their ſide the Scriptures, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, Fathers, Councells, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and for that euery one which was againſt them, was euer accounted, &amp; reputed for an Heretike. And the ſame Catholikes were euer taken as the trounke, or as the bodye of the tree, and all others bearing the name of Chriſtians, as braunches, or boughs cutte off the ſame tree. Nowe all the worlde knoweth, that whoſoeuer in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny age, was a member of the Romane Church, &amp; vnder the obedience of the high Biſhoppe thereof, hee was euer taken for a Catholike, and ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, although in theſe our daies it hath pleaſed the proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to cal ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13600:11"/>
by the name of Papiſts, which indeed is all one with the name Catholikes, for that it ſignifieth ſuch as followe &amp; imbrace the Doctrine of that Church which hath for her head vnder Chriſt the Pope. And it is not amiſſe as Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Hom. 33. in acta.</note> to be named of them who gouerne the Church in Chriſtes ſteede, ſo that they take not their name of any particular man, as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes doe. But yet the Catholikes are not called Papiſts, but only of a fewe Lutheranes in <hi>Germany,</hi> and of ſome others their adherents in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries neere about, for in <hi>Greece, Aſia, Affrike,</hi> &amp; in the <hi>Indies,</hi> as in <hi>Italy, Spain, Sicily,</hi> and in other countries of <hi>Europe,</hi> the name of Papiſtes is vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. The name therefore of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts is no name commonly vſed, but only of a fewe, and neuer heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Luther</hi> inuented it, for that hee coulde not call them after the proper name of any one man, becauſe there was neuer anye ſuch in the Church, which either brought vp anye newe Doctrine, or chainged the Religion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13600:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of his Predeceſſours, whereas contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, heretikes haue euer taken their names of ſome one who began that hereſie: as the Neſtorians, of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> the Pelagians, of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> Lutherans, of <hi>Luther,</hi> Caluiniſts, of <hi>Caluin, &amp;c.</hi> And although <hi>Luther</hi> tearmed them Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, yet knewe he ſo well in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that they euer had beene, and ought to be called Catholikes, as that he cauſed his folowers to chainge their Creede, in ſaying:<note place="margin">Briſt. Mo. 1</note> 
               <hi>I beleeue the Chriſtian Church,</hi> and not:<note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>I beleeue the Catholike Church:</hi> for feare leaſt they ſhould bee thought to confeſſe that they belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was called Catholike. And it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the Proteſtants knowe in their owne conſciences, the name of heretikes to bee ſo proper to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as that in their tranſlations of the Bible, where the name Heretike occurreth, they put in place of it, <hi>a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is the author of ſects:</hi> aſſuring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that the Reader finding the worde <hi>Heretike,</hi> or <hi>Hereſie,</hi> woulde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently iudge it to be meant of them.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13600:12"/>
As for their own name, whereby they tearme themſelues proteſtants (which name they take from certaine <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranes</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> who firſt named them ſelues ſo, differing, and diſagreeing altogether from theſe Proteſtants in Doctrine) it is newe, and neuer heard of before in the world, and of the ſame quality and condition, that the name <hi>Zwinglians</hi> is of. And therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the ſaying of Saint <hi>Hierome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aduerſ. Lucif. Chryſoſt. in act. hom 33. &amp; Iuſt. in Tryph.</note> 
               <hi>If any where thou heare, them, which are ſayed to be of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>to be tearmed, not of our</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>but of ſome other, as</hi> Marcionites. Valentinians, Hil-bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>or</hi> Fielde-breethren, <hi>be thou ſure, that they are not the Church of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>but the Synagogue of</hi> Anti-chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="reason">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13600:12"/>
            <head>THE THIRD REASON. Vnity and Conſent.</head>
            <p>THE Catholike Romane Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beeing receiued by ſo manie Nations, in <hi>Affrica, Aſia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Europa,</hi> &amp; in this laſt age in both the <hi>Indies,</hi> hath notwithſtanding ſuch varietie of wits, ſuch diuerſity of manners, ſuch multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of tongues and languages, ſuch diſtance of places, ſuch numbers of matters to be beleeued, yet euer kept Vnity, &amp; Concord in ſuch peaceable and conſonant manner, as neuer anie one in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> which are the vttermoſt parts of the weſt-world, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, or diſagreed in anye point of Doctrine, concerning Faith, from him which liued in the vtmoſt parts of the Eaſt. But whoſoeuer they be, or in what place, or region ſoeuer they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in al the world, if they be catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes or papiſts (if you will call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo) they all haue one Faith, one Beleefe, one Seruice, one number of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13600:13"/>
one Obedience, one Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all, with other like pointes of Vnion, and Vnitie, which maketh a generall vniformitie alſo in the peace of mens mindes, and to be briefe they haue all one heart, and one ſoule: But on the other ſide,<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> if you look into the doinges of Proteſtantes, you ſhall ſee ſuch diſcentions, ſuch diuiſions, ſuch ſchiſmes, ſuch contrariety of opinions; as the like was neuer among the <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> among the <hi>Eutychians,</hi> among the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> among the <hi>Nestorians,</hi> among the <hi>Valentinians,</hi> no nor yet amongeſt the moſt iarring Heretikes that euer were. So as you may plainely beholde in <hi>Luther</hi> his ſeed the ſelfe-ſame thing that the Poets faine of <hi>Cadmus</hi> his ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; you may ſee the <hi>Madianytes</hi> &amp; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekites</hi> in one tent againſt the people of God;<note place="margin">Ouid. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam. lib. 3. Iudic. 7.</note> builders of the tower <hi>Babell,</hi> accuſars of chaſte <hi>Suſanna:</hi> for they are not only different, and deuided from the generall body of Catholickes in Chriſtendome, with whom they were vnited heretofore: but amongſt them ſelues they haue implacable warres. I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13600:13"/>
would you did but ſee, what I haue ſeene in theſe Countries, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the deadly hatreds, contentions, and diſcentions of <hi>Luther</hi> his ofspring: as of the <hi>Muntzerans, Anabaptiſts, Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, Steblerians, Sabbataries, Clanculari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> or <hi>Gartenbrijder, Manifestarians, Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians, Commonholders, Byſlipers, How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Anabaptiſts, Dauidgeorgians, Memno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, Polygamiſtes, Signifiers, Figurers, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lewers, Pledgers, Preſentaries, Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſts, Iudaiſts, Neuterſacramentaries, Image breakers, Zelous Lutherans, Soft Lutherans,</hi> or <hi>Interimiſtes, New-Arrians, Trinitaries, Hell-maisters, Hell-tormentors, Antidaemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Amſdorfians, Antadiaphoristes, Antoſiandrians, Anti-Swenckefeldians, Anti Caluiniſts, Hand-impoſitors, Biſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarians, Sacerdotales, Inuiſibiliſts, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turians, Adiaphoriſtes, Triſacramentarians, Quadriſacramentarians, Luthero Caluiniſts, Semioſiandrians, Maioriſts, Penitentiarians, Noui-Pelagians, Politicke-Lutheranes, Swenckefeldians, Oſiandrians, Stancarians, Antiſtancarians, New-Manichees, Stern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergers,</hi> and of ſuch like: all which haue ſucked their errors out of the dregges
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13600:14"/>
of <hi>Luthers</hi> Doctrine, and yet forſooth, will be ſound Proteſtantes all. And what diuiſions you haue there in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> you may in ſome ſort know, who doe (as I thinke) now and then heare preachers of different doctrine. What combats your Biſhops, Councellours, &amp; moderate ſort of Proteſtants haue to defende their Parlimentarie Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the QVEENES Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges as they tearme it, againſt Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, browniſts, &amp; other ſuchlike good fellowes, that by ſhew of Scriptures impugne it, you can not but know &amp; ſee vvith your eyes. Neyther can it be aunſwered, that the Sectes heere rehearſed differ one from another on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in matters of ſmall moment, for they differ and diſagree in vveightie pointes of our Saluation, as might heere eaſilie be declared, but that it vvould not benifit this mine intended breuitie ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>This Vnitie of CATHOLICKES, and diſcorde of PROTESTANTES, moſt manifeſtlie ſheweth, that as the Apoſtles vvere they, for whome our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13600:14"/>
SAVIOVR prayed to his FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER, and vvas heard of him: <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Father, keepe them in thy name, whome thou haſte giuen mee, that they may be one, as wee alſo be one,</hi> Iohn ſeauenteene: ſo they of the CATHOLIKE ROMAN Religion, be they, for vvhome in the vvordes following hee prayed, and vvas heard: <hi>Not for them doe I aſke one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo for them, which ſhall beleeue, by theyr preaching in mee, that all may be one, as thou Father in mee, and I in thee, that alſo they in vs, may be one:</hi> and hereof it neceſſarilie followeth, that they be of the true CHVRCH, for that none but they obſerue and keepe the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vvhich hee obtained for them of his Heauenlie FATHER.<note place="margin">Aug. l. 18. de ciuit. dei. C. 41.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurelie it can not proceede but from the HOLIE GHOST, that all Sacred vvriters of the CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKE ROMAN CHVRCH, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though being men of diuers Nations, Times, and Languages, yet haue ſo vvonderfullie conſented, and agreed amongeſt themſelues, as wee ſee they haue done.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13600:15"/>And laſtlie, it is wonderfull to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, how all decrees of lawfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and of Popes doe agree in all points of Doctrine, one with another, although they were made by diuers men, in diuers places, at ſundrie times, vpon diuers occaſions, &amp; againſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, not only moſt different, but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes contrarie one to another. This, no doubt, is the finger of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="reason">
            <head>THE IIII. REASON. Conuerſion of Countries.</head>
            <p>IT is moſt plaine and manifeſt, that all Countries, which euer beleeued in Chriſt, were firſt conuerted to his faith by ſuch, as eyther were preciſely ſent, or at the leaſt-wiſe had their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie from the Pope, which liued in the time, in which they were conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. This thing is ſo openly ſet downe in the Hiſtorie of the firſt conuerſion of euery Countrie, as no Proteſtant, were he neuer ſo impudent, can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13600:15"/>
bluſhing denie it. True it is, that Heretiks haue corrupted ſuch as were Catholikes before, but that they euer conuerted any Heathen Nation to Chriſtianitie can neuer be ſhewed. I know very well that <hi>Iohn Caluin</hi> to get glorie, ſent certaine of his Miniſters into new-found landes, but I neuer could heare that any of them euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted ſo much as one ſillie woman to their Ghoſpell in thoſe partes. The truth is, their agreement in doctrine was ſo great, that one deſtroying an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others buildings, they became laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtocks to the Heathens, &amp; ſo were glad to depart with ſhame. But who knoweth not that the Catholikes, as they haue conuerted all to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that euer were Chriſtians: ſo in this age they haue brought infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to the Chriſtian faith in the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, by the meanes and labours of the moſt happie &amp; holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the holy Order of <hi>S. Frauncis,</hi> of <hi>S. Dominick,</hi> &amp; of the bleſſed Society of IESVS, which bleſſed Religious men in our owne Countrie there of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13600:16"/>
England, onlie in regard of theyr Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred function, are executed as Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. And haue not theſe I pray you theyr authoritie from ROME? I will not here ſpeake of the infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Miracles vvrought by Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes in the conuerſion of countries, &amp; namely of thoſe which are now done in both the Indies by the Holie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers aforeſaid, for that I reſerue that matter for his proper place, but I vvould aduiſe you here diligentlie to weigh the ſequele of the Aſſertion of the Proteſtants; how that if Papiſtes be not true Chriſtians, &amp; of the right religion, then doth it neceſſarilie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that neither Spaniards, nor Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingales, nor Sardinians, nor Sicilians, nor Italians, nor Germanes, nor Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyluanians, nor Hungarians, nor Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians, nor Danes, nor Flemminges, nor Scots, nor Iriſh, nor Engliſh, no nor any Nation vnder Heauen had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer true Religion, before Fryar <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> married <hi>Nonne Bore,</hi> before <hi>Iohn Caluine</hi> runne away to <hi>Geneua,</hi> before <hi>Peeter Martyr</hi> vvith his Fuſtelugges
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13600:16"/>
came to teach at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and before a number of ſuch like good compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ledde only by ſenſualitie, &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall zeale diſhodded themſelues, and became ſuch ſpectacles to the worlde as euerie man knoweth. Which thing to affirme, is flatlie to denie Chriſt, &amp; all Chriſtianity, as I ſhewed in my firſt Reaſon. And ſurely I am greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Catholike Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Heauenly maner vſed by the profeſſors thereof in gayning ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to Almightie GOD, for that I ſee them neyther to ſpare goodes, nor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, no nor theyr owne liues, ſo that they may vvinne people to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>GREGORYE the thirteenth Pope of that name in theſe our dayes, ſpent all the renennewes of the Popedome in founding SEMINARIES &amp; COL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEDGES in diuers Landes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, thereby to reſtore the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion.</p>
            <p>Manie Holie and Religious Prieſts doe goe dayly into <hi>Germany,</hi> into <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> into <hi>Greece,</hi> into <hi>Palestina,</hi> into
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13600:17"/>
               <hi>Aegypt,</hi> into <hi>Syria,</hi> into <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> into <hi>Africa,</hi> into <hi>Moſcouia,</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> and into other heretical &amp; heathen countries, yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues to all daungers by ſea, and land, and to all worldly miſeries, hauing mortified all theyr carnall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, renounced all riches, honors, and kindred, and hauing made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues moſt ready for their graue, and conſequently for another world, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued only by the zeale of ſauing ſoules. And it mooueth mee not a little to ſee vvhat patience, mildneſſe, and quietneſſe theſe men vſe in all theyr dooinges. And I ſee alſo on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, that no proteſtant euer had ſo great zeale of his Religion, as that he would for ſpreading abroade the ſame, forgoe any worldly commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, either by founding Seminaries, or Colleges in Countries, or by going, or ſending where any difficulty or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was, but as one wholly reſpecting this worlde, he walloweth in wealth, &amp; pleaſures at home, or if by any acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent he be compelled to flie into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13600:17"/>
Countries, hee may not trauaile except his preatie parnell goe vvith him; but ſuch a one to goe ſimplie, &amp; as they ſay, <hi>bona fide,</hi> to conuert others was yet neuer ſeene. And if by anie occaſion offered vnto ſuch, they goe about to plant theyr Ghoſpell anie vvhere, they doe it in ſuch a turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and mutinous maner, and not by Epiſtles after Saint <hi>Paules</hi> vſe, but by Piſtols as <hi>Beza</hi> did, as euerie one may ſee what ſpirit pricketh them forward. Neyther doe they take anie other courſe in theyr proceedinges, but to deſtroy States and Kingdomes, &amp; to diſplace lawfull Monarchies and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, as the <hi>Low-Countries, Germany,</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> can ſufficientlie witneſſe, and euer theyr beginning is of Pride and Enuie, as <hi>Luthers</hi> vvas; or by abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them-ſelues in theyr former e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as Sir <hi>Iohn Caluin</hi> did, or by yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues ſlaues to ambition, as they did in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or by following Luſt and Leacherie, or of ſome ſuch like brutiſh occaſion, and neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede vpon anie good ground, vſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13600:18"/>
their religion only as a <hi>ſerueturne,</hi> when other meanes faile to atchieue theyr vnlawfull deſires. It is plaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my iudgement, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks are they, who euer fiſhed ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie and ſyncerely, with Saint <hi>Peeters</hi> Net, and therein haue encloſed my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous multitudes of fiſhes, and that the Proteſtantes, by theyr extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and late angling haue caught none, but ſuch as were in a better, and more ſound maner taken before. And although <hi>Freculphus</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">In Chron. tom. 2. li. 4 cap. 20.</note> that the <hi>Arrian</hi> heretikes conuerted the whole nation of the <hi>Gothes</hi> from Paganyſme to the Faith, in the time of <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour;<note place="margin">socrates. lib. 4. cap. 27. sozom. l. 6 cap. 37. Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. lib 4. cap. vlt.</note> yet it appeareth by <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Sozomenus,</hi> and <hi>Theodoretus,</hi> that the greateſt part of thoſe <hi>Gothes</hi> were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Chriſtians before, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſeduced by the <hi>Arrians:</hi> for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes cannot poſsiblie conuert anie to ſuch faith as may make the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted better then they were before, for that they hauing indeede the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in ſome ſort, yet haue not the true ſenſe thereof, vvhich properly is the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13600:18"/>
ſword of the ſpirit, and the wordes are rather the ſcabard, in which the ſword is ſheathed. And therefore they fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only with the ſcabard, without the ſword, cannot wound the harts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels. And no meruaile though they peruert Catholikes, for that men are prone to libertie, and to looſeneſſe of life, which by ſuch doctrine is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. So that they are indeed moſt apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by S. <hi>Augustine</hi> likened vnto Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges,<note place="margin">lib. 13. con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra fauſt. cap. 12.</note> which gather together young ones which they begot not; whereas contrariwiſe the Holy Church is a moſt fertle Doue, which continuallie bringeth forth new Pigeons.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="reason">
            <head>
               <hi>THE FIFT REASON,</hi> largenes of Dominion through the multitude of Beleeuers.</head>
            <p>THE Church vvhich the <hi>Meſsias</hi> was to plant, muſt be (as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) diſperſed throughout al <hi>nations</hi> &amp; <hi>kingdomes,</hi> as the Holy Prophets moſt plainely foreſhewed, and namely the Royall Prophet, ſpeaking of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and Preachers, vvhich ſhould Succeede them, ſaieth:<note place="margin">Pſal 18.</note> 
               <hi>Theyr ſounde
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13600:19"/>
went foorth into all partes of the Earth, and theyr wordes vnto the endes of the circle of the earth.</hi> And moſt manifeſtlie doth he foretell the largeneſſe of Chriſtian Religion in the 71. Pſalme. And S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the foure beaſts,<note place="margin">Apoc. c. 5.</note> &amp; the foure and twentie Elders fall downe before the Lambe, ſinging thus: <hi>Thou art wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Lord to take the Booke, and to open the ſeales therof, for thou haſt bin ſlaine, &amp; haſt redeemed vs to God in thy Blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 7.</note> 
               <hi>out of euery Tribe, &amp; people, &amp; Language, &amp; Nation:</hi> &amp; in another place: <hi>After theſe things, ſaith hee, I ſaw a great companie, which no man was able to nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, of all Nations, &amp; Tribes, and Peoples, and Tongues.</hi> Theſe thinges with manie ſuch like in Holy writ are no wiſe verefied in any Religion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heauen, but onely in the <hi>Romaine</hi> Catholike Church; for that none but it (as euerie man knoweth) hath had any large ſcope to account vpon in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny age. And it hath beene for theſe thouſand yeares at the leaſt through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out both the Hemyſpheres, in ſuch ſort as the ſunne ſtretcheth not his beames further then it doth, and hath
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13600:19"/>
done: yea, there is no tongue nor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor climate in the vvorlde, which hath not heard of, &amp; in ſome meaſure receaued the Catholike Romaine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Neither can the Proteſtantes ſay, that the Church now beginneth to flouriſh, and to dilate it ſelfe in the worlde after ſo many ages; for that now it is growen olde and aged, as is moſt plaine, &amp; to ſay that ſhe increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not in her younge yeares, but now in her olde age is to make her a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. She muſt therefore of neceſsitie, haue growen, &amp; increaſed, &amp; occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if not all the world, yet no doubt the greateſt part thereof, and ſo hath the Catholike Romaine Church, and none but ſhe done:<note place="margin">Colloſſ. 1.</note> for in the Apoſtles time ſhee began to fructifie in all the world. And in <hi>S. Irenaeus</hi> his time,<note place="margin">Irenaeus. l. 1. cap. 3. Tertul. li. contra Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos. ca. 4. Cyprian de vuit. ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſ. Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſ. lib. de humanit.</note> ſhee was ſpreade all ouer the vvorld then knowen, as ſhe was afterwards in <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> his time, and in the dayes of <hi>S. Cyprian, Athanaſius, Chriſoſtome, Hierome, Augustine, Theodoretus, Leo the great,</hi> and <hi>Proſper,</hi> vvho in his booke <hi>De Ingratis</hi> hath theſe wordes.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13600:20"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">verbi Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoſt. &amp; Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eron. in Mat. 24. Aug. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 78. &amp; 80. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſychium. Theod. lib de legibus Leo. Mag. ſer. 1. de S S. Petro &amp; Paulo.</note>Sedes Roma Petri, quae pastoralis honoris,</l>
                  <l>Facta caput mundo, quic quid nos poſsidit armis,</l>
                  <l>Religione tenet. <hi>Which thus may be Engliſhed.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rome, Peters ſeate, whoſe Biſhop is of Prelates Peereles Lord,</l>
                  <l>Religion Lady makes of all, which armes do not afford.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>But the Proteſtantes peraduenture, will graunt that the true Church flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in thoſe dayes, but not after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vntill this age, in which they haue reformed the ſame: yet is it moſt manifeſt, that it flouriſhed afterwards euen vntill this our time, no leſſe then it did before, if not more: for in Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> his dayes it was ſpread all ouer the world, as appeareth by his Epiſtles to the Biſhoppes of the Eaſt, of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frike, Spayne, Fraunce, England, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilie. And by Saint <hi>Bede</hi> in cap. 6. can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic:<note place="margin">In vita S. Bernardi. lib. 2. ca. 7.</note> as alſo by Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting before <hi>Rogerius</hi> King of Sicilie, auouched that in thoſe dayes, the Eaſt, all the Weſt, Fraunce Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, England, Spaniardes, and manie barbarous nations obeyed the Biſhop of Rome. And in theſe dayes, it is all ouer Italie, all ouer Spayne, and in Fraunce, in moſt parts of Germanie, in Poleland, Boheme, beſides Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13600:20"/>
Hungarie, Greece, Syria, Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia, Aegypt, in vvhich Landes are manie Catholikes; and in the nevve world it flouriſheth mightily, in al the foure parts of the world; Eaſtward in the Indies; Weſtward in America: Northward in Iaponia, Southward in Braſilia, and in the vttermoſt parts of Afrike. And to name ſomewhat more in particular ſome Countries, in which it is happely receaued of many, if not vniuerſally of all, but yet in many la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds it is receaued of the greateſt parte of the inhabitants, in <hi>Goa,</hi> in <hi>Malabar,</hi> in <hi>Cochin,</hi> in <hi>Bazain,</hi> in <hi>Cola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> in <hi>Tana,</hi> in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> in <hi>Ciaul,</hi> in <hi>Coran,</hi> in <hi>Salſetta,</hi> in <hi>Peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caria,</hi> in <hi>Manar,</hi> in <hi>Trauancor,</hi> in <hi>Cogiro,</hi> in <hi>Bugen,</hi> in <hi>Cicungo,</hi> in <hi>Cicugne,</hi> in <hi>Oian,</hi> in <hi>Gomotto,</hi> in <hi>Genſura,</hi> in <hi>Xichi,</hi> in <hi>Ormuz,</hi> in <hi>Ternate,</hi> in <hi>Momoia,</hi> in <hi>Ambonio,</hi> in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cazar,</hi> in <hi>Cerignano,</hi> in <hi>Siligan,</hi> in <hi>Butuan,</hi> in <hi>Pimiliran,</hi> in <hi>Camigu,</hi> in <hi>Supa,</hi> in <hi>Sian,</hi> in <hi>Bacian,</hi> in <hi>Solar,</hi> in <hi>Malacca,</hi> in <hi>Tidor,</hi> in <hi>Selebi,</hi> and in the Ilandes of S. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazo,</hi> S. <hi>Domingo, Madera,</hi> and in all thoſe innumerable Iſlandes, vvhich the King of <hi>Spayne</hi> there poſſeſſeth:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13600:21"/>
So that the Catholike Romaine Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion hath had, and hath yet a far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſway in the world, then any other religion euer had, or hath. And wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie it is to be noted, that in no land nor countrie vnder Heauen euer was, or is, any perſecution, of any moment againſt Papiſts (as you terme them) or againſt the Prieſts of that religion, in regard that they be Papiſts, or Prieſts made by authoritie from the Sea of Rome, but only in England. And in verie deede, the vvhole world doth wonder, that little England dare, and is not aſhamed to doe that, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was ſeene in the world before: for let a Seminary prieſt (as they cal him) keepe him out of England, and hee is ſafe enough in any region vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. This I ſay by the way, for that it greeueth me at the very hart, to heare that my deare country doth perſecute that religion, which all the world hath ioifully embraced, or at the leaſt, doth willingly tolerate, as though ſhe were wiſer then all the world beſides is, or euer hath beene, or then al her Elders.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13600:21"/>
Or, as though <hi>Engliſhe</hi> Proteſtantes knewe, and ſawe more, than all the whole Learned men of Chriſtendome haue done for ſo many ages together. And I pray you, tell me, if an hearbe ſhould be preſented to you to eat, that al learned Phyſitions for a thowſand yeeres together, haue iudged to bee ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke poiſon, &amp; only ſome one or two of later yeeres, haue begun to teache the contrary, without actuall experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence whether it be ſo or no, but onlie by diſcourſe, and newe arguments, of their owne braine, would you abſtaine to eate it or no? Or if an action ſhould be offered you there in <hi>England,</hi> which by all old Lawyers iudgement of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times hath beene taken for high-treaſon <hi>Ipſo facto,</hi> &amp; conſequently loſſe of life, and lands, though ſome newer lawyers were of contrary opinion that nowe it is not, woulde you not looke twiſe before you would leape, except you were out of your wittes? But in this other caſe, although all auncient Diuines, and Doctours, for aboue a thowſand yeres together, haue taught
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13600:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Catholike Romane Religion, to be true indeede, and only Friar <hi>Luther</hi> a looſe Apoſtata, and Sir <hi>Iohn Caluin,</hi> a ſeare-backt Prieſt for Sodomy, haue begun in our daies to teache the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for feare of beeing puniſhed by the Magiſtrates of the ſaid Catholike Religion, for wicked, and badde life, yet will they Proteſtants ruſhe out, &amp; caſt at all, and will hazarde Hell, and all Eternity of tormentes thereon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending. Who will denie this to bee headlong, and hare-braine dealing? Surely this vniuerſal conſent of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, againſt two or three ſo contemptible authors of nouelties, are more than ſufficient to induce anye man of reaſon to looke about him, and to conſider what hee doth, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he may aduenture his ſoule vpon ſuch inequality of teſtimonies, as this is betweene two, or three Nouellants, and twenty millions of holy &amp; graue auncientes, and no doubt in Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter hall this difference of witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes woulde preuaile with anye equall, and diſcreet iudge or iurie. Neither
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13600:22"/>
may the Proteſtantes nowe at length glory in their great number, as ſome of them haue donne, for that their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is there in England, &amp; in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and ſome thereof in Irelande,<note place="margin">Apol. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Ang.</note> and in the Lowe-countries, &amp; in ſome parts of Germany, and a fewe of them in Fraunce, for they neuer yet paſſed into Aſia, nor into Affrica, nor into Greece, nor into many places of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, much leſſe into the Indies. But indeed if you rightly ſcanne their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, you ſhall finde that your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion Proteſtantine of Englande, is no where in the worlde elſe, &amp; that Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe ſeruice contained in your boke of Common praier is vnknowen, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of all other Nations, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnder the cope of Heauen. So that in very deed the doctrine of your Proteſtantes is taught, or receaued, no where but in Englande, and the Puritane Doctrine of Scotlande (the contrarietie thereof duelye conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) is no where but in Scotlande, the Lutherane Doctrine taught in Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, is no where but in Denmarke,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13600:23"/>
and in a fewe places of <hi>Germany,</hi> the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine Doctrine taught in the Low-countries, is no where but in the Low-countries, and the like may be ſaid of other ſectes.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I doe heere conſider with my ſelfe, if I ſhould refuſe the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Romane Religion, ſo vniuerſallie taught, receaued &amp; profeſſed through out all the worlde ſo many ages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and embrace any of theſe newe ſilly ſectes, aduenturing my ſoul ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, what all my progenitours &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours, if they were here againe, and ſawe me doe ſo, would ſay vnto me, I geſſe they would vſe ſuch ſpeeches as theſe: what doeſt thou condemne all our iudgementes, and doings? Doeſt thou maligne that Religion, which we ſo highly eſteemed and ſought to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce? Doeſt thou ſende vs al to hel and damnation? Wilt thou iudge thy ſelfe wiſer and more in Gods fauour than any of vs were? And many ſuch like ſpeeches I thinke they would vſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="reason">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:13600:23"/>
            <head>THE SIXT REASON. Miracles.</head>
            <p>True miracles were neuer wrought but by them, who were of true religion, for that they are donne only by the power of God. Now it is ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that there hath beene almoſt an infinite number of myracles wrought by thoſe who were of the Catholike Romane Religion, and neuer any by them who were not of that Church, ſince Chriſtes time, as he who ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, may be proued no leſſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ſhameleſſe, than he who ſhal denie, that euer there was any Maſſe ſaide in times paſt in <hi>England,</hi> or that euer there were any warres betweene Turkes and Chriſtians, or that ther be any ſuch countries as the Eaſt &amp; Weſt Indies. Which things if a man ſhould deny, would he not of all men be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not only impudent, but madde, drunken, or a foole? And ſurely the one is no leſſe knowne by al approued
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13600:24"/>
writers, and eie witneſſes than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For as in the Goſpell, and in the Actes, the holy Scriptures witneſſe, that miracles were wrought by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, ſo doe moſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued authors of euery age vntil this day teſtifie and recorde the continuance of the working thereof in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Romane Church, the which Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors for the moſt part were eie-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the ſaide miracles, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. In the ſecond age were wrought thoſe wonderful miracles by the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Souldiers in the armie of <hi>M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tert. in lib ad Scap. &amp; in apol. c. 5 Euſeb. lib. 5. hiſt. c. 5. Oroſ. lib. 7. hiſt. c. 15</note> which <hi>Tertullian, Euſebius, Oroſius,</hi> &amp; the Emperoor himſelfe haue recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. In the third age were the miracles of <hi>Gregorius Thaumaturgus,</hi> witneſſes S. <hi>Baſil lib. de spiritu ſancto Cap.</hi> 29. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen in vita eius. Hierom de viris illuſtrib. Ruffinus lib.</hi> 7. <hi>hiſt. cap.</hi> 25. In the fourth of S. <hi>Anthony, Hilarion, Martine, Nicolas,</hi> and of others. In the fifte, thoſe which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſetteth downe <hi>lib.</hi> 22. <hi>de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Cap.</hi> 8. In the ſixt, thoſe which S. <hi>Gregory</hi> maketh mention of, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>dial. Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. In the ſeauenth, thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13600:24"/>
which were done in <hi>England,</hi> in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſame <hi>Greg. li.</hi> 9. <hi>ep.</hi> 58. And by venerable <hi>Bede. l.</hi> 1. <hi>hiſt. Ca.</hi> 31. In the eight, the miracles of S. <hi>Cutbert,</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> alſo <hi>Bede. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>hiſt. &amp;</hi> 5. In the ninth, the miracles of <hi>Tharaſius,</hi> writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by <hi>Ignat. Nicen.</hi> &amp; of others. In the tenth, the miracles of S. <hi>Romuald.</hi> recorded by S. <hi>Pet. Damian:</hi> of S. <hi>Wenceſlaus,</hi> &amp; of others which <hi>Surius</hi> writeth. In the eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th, the miracles of S. <hi>Edward</hi> k. &amp; vir. of S. <hi>Anſ.</hi> &amp; of others In the twelfth, the miracles of S. <hi>Mal.</hi> S <hi>Barn.</hi> &amp; of others. In the thirteenth, the miracles of S. <hi>Fran.</hi> S. <hi>Dom.</hi> S. <hi>Bonauent.</hi> S. S. <hi>Celeſt.</hi> &amp; of others. In the fourteenth, the miracles of S. <hi>Bernardine,</hi> S. <hi>Kather.</hi> of <hi>Sieuna,</hi> &amp; of others. In the fifteenth, the miracles of S. <hi>Vinc.</hi> S. <hi>Ant.</hi> &amp; of others. And laſt of al in this our ſixteenth age are the miracles of the glorious S. <hi>Fran. de Paula,</hi> of the holy Ieſuit <hi>Zauer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de vtil. cred. cap. 17. &amp; lib. cont. ep. fund. cap. 4.</note> in the Indies, &amp; of many moe. And therfore I ſay vnto you out of S. <hi>Ang. I am bound &amp; tied in the Catholike Church by the band or chaine of myracles.</hi> And I am bolde conſidering, and moſte ſteedefaſtlye
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13600:25"/>
beleuing theſe infinite glorious myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of all times and ages in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Romane Church, to crye out to Almighty God, with <hi>Richard de S. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de trin. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Lord, if it be not true which we beleeue, thou hast deceaued vs: for theſe haue beene confirmed in vs by ſuch ſignes and woonders as could not bee wrought but by thee.</hi> But on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part, neuer any Proteſtant coulde worke any myracle at all, but aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make ſome ſhewe thereof, to make their Doctrine the more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their followers, felt the iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengement of God, who turned all to their ſhame and confuſion, as hee did by <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Egeſippus lib. 3. de excid. hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſol. ca. 2.</note> by <hi>Cyrola</hi> the patriarke of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> as witneſſeth <hi>Grego. Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>hiſt, Franc. cap.</hi> 3. by the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts. Optatus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contr. Parmen.</hi> And in our daies by <hi>Luther,</hi> endeuoring to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe a wenche, and by <hi>Caluin</hi> going about to delude his diſciples, as you may reade in <hi>Hierom Bolſec. in vit. Caluin cap.</hi> 13.<note place="margin">Vid. Staph in abſ. reſp</note> And therefore they are moſt fooliſhe and miſerably inconſiderate, who beleeue theſe newe fellowes, not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13600:25"/>
beeing able to quicken a flea, &amp; leaue the doctrine of the Catholike Church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed with innumerable miracles.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="reason">
            <head>THE VII. REASON. Viſions, and the gifte of Prophecie.</head>
            <p>AS TRVE Miracles neuer were wrought but by them who were of the true Church, ſo heauenly Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the gifte of Prophecie, were neuer founde to bee but in the ſame. And therefore the holye Apoſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt other thinges which he vſeth to commend his Doctrine, &amp; himſelfe to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> againſt Heretickes,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> and falſe Apoſtles, he bringeth in this as one ſaying. <hi>Now will I come to Viſions and Reuelations of our Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> alleageth for confirmation of his preaching the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſfiguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our lord in the mount which he ſawe,<note place="margin">Mat. 17. Act. 10. &amp; 11.</note> &amp; calleth it a Viſion, he had a Viſion of a ſheet with al kind of beaſts in it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was to deale with the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> And for the trueth of Religion, and confirmation
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13600:26"/>
of that which they did, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageth the prophecie of <hi>Ioell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel. cap. 2</note> who ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth amongſt other thinges: <hi>Your young men ſhall ſee Viſions,</hi> and to bee briefe, of this ſort is the whole boke of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyps.</hi> So that to ſee theſe kind of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Viſions, and thereby to foretel things moſt certainly, is only amongſt them who are of the true Church. For although there haue beene prophecies amongeſt the <hi>Heathens,</hi> yet were they not vndoubtedly true, as the Oracles of <hi>Apollo,</hi> &amp; ſuch like illuſions, except they were for the confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of right Religion, as the prophecies of the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bills,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 5. hiſt. cap. 16. &amp; 18.</note> and of <hi>Balaam.</hi> And the ſame may be ſaide of heretikes, as of <hi>Montanus,</hi> of <hi>Luther,</hi> of <hi>Muncer,</hi> and of ſuch like, who loke vpon them to prophecie ſome to their vtter ſhame, &amp; ſome to their own deſtruction. But the Catho. Romane Church hath had in it in all ages thoſe which had true Viſions,<note place="margin">Cochlaeus in actis Lutheri.</note> and the gifte of true prophecie, as <hi>Agabus. Act.</hi> 11. <hi>Gregory Thaumaturge,</hi> ſo <hi>Baſil. li. de spiritu ſancto Cap.</hi> 29. S. <hi>Anthony,</hi> the Abbote <hi>Iohn,</hi> of whom, ſee S. <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de ciuit.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13600:26"/>
Cap.</hi> 26. S. <hi>Monica,</hi> ſee <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Confeſ. Cap.</hi> 11. S. <hi>Benedicte</hi> ſee <hi>Gregor. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>dial. Cap.</hi> 15. S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> ſee <hi>in eius vita. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. S. <hi>Frauncis,</hi> ſee <hi>in eius vita Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentura,</hi> with many others, for ſeldome was ther any who had the gifte of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, but the ſame had this gifte alſo. And in theſe daies, I knowe diuerſe and ſundry Papiſts, (as you cal them) who haue ſeen vndoubtedly wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Viſions, which perhaps you maye ſee recorded hereafter, with ſufficient and irrefragable teſtimony.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="reason">
            <head>THE VIII. REASON. Scriptures.</head>
            <p>NEither may here the Proteſtant reply, and ſay, that the Papiſtes builde vpon Miracles, Viſions, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, and vpon ſuch like, but not vpon the WORDE, for al that they alleadge are moſt agreeable to the worde of God. Neither doe they teach any Doctrine but ſuch as is deriued out of the holy Bible, &amp; for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13600:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thereof, they are not compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to denye certaine partes of Gods holy Booke, as the Proteſtantes, and their predeceſſours, heretiks, haue bin inforced to do. The <hi>Manichees,</hi> for that their hereſies were ſo manifeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by the Goſpel of Saint <hi>Mathewe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. l 28. con Fauſt cap. 2. &amp; de vtil. cred. cap 3.</note> and by the <hi>Actes</hi> of the Apoſtles, as they coulde coine no aunſwere, nor other ſhifte, they denyed them to bee Scripture. The <hi>Ebinites,</hi> becauſe the Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> diſproued moſt plainelye Cyrcumciſion, which they maintained, denied them to be Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Luther</hi> reiected the Epiſtle of S. <hi>Iames,</hi> becauſe it was ſo plaine againſt the doctrine, of onely Faith. His of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring refuſed the bookes of <hi>Tobias,</hi> of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> of the <hi>Machabees,</hi> and of ſome others, becauſe in them is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught the Doctrine of the cuſtody of Aungells, of Free-will, of Praier for the Faithfull Soules departed, and of Prayer to Saints, al wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch they deny, and therefore muſt they needes denie thoſe parts of the holy Bible. For he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes euer framed the Bible to their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13600:27"/>
opinions, chainging, wreſting, paring, &amp; ſometimes flatly reiecting, al which made ouerplainely againſt ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as they deuiſed, and ſo doe moſt impudentlye the Proteſtantes nowe. Whereas the Catholikes euer ſquared their Doctrine by the line and the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of the Worde of her Spouſe, and therefore neuer had cauſe to reiecte the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otte of the holy Bible, and at one worde, the Catholikes followe the Bible, but the Proteſtantes force the Bible to followe them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="reason">
            <head>THE IX. REASON. Councells.</head>
            <p>THe Church of God hath euer bin accuſtomed, when any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie did ſpring vp therein, to gather a Councell of Biſhoppes, Prelates, and of other Learned Men, in which the trueth was approued, and the hereſie condemned. And whoſoeuer were condemned by ſuch Councells, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the See Apoſtolike, were euer deemed, and in very deede, were
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13600:28"/>
heretiks, &amp; for ſuch at length were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of all men, &amp; in the end vaniſhed away. So were the <hi>Arrians</hi> condemned in the Nyceene Counſel, the <hi>Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in the Councel of Conſtantinople, the <hi>Neſtorians</hi> in the Epheſyne, the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychians</hi> in the Chalcedonian, &amp; others in other Councels. Al which heretiks, although they flouriſhed for a time, and drewe manye people, yea Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, States, &amp; Countries after them, yet in time they came to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, &amp; the councels which condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were vniuerſally embraced. And no doubt the late famouſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent, which by the ſame auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity &amp; order hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants &amp; other ſectaries for heretiks, will in time be euery where receiued, and theſe newe fellowes by it anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized, will vtterlye vaniſhe away. For indeed if a man conſider the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter throughly, he ſhal plainly perceiue that theſe ſects haue no likelihoode of continuance, by reaſon they haue no meanes to gather a Councel, &amp; much leſſe to decide matters therein, if it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13600:28"/>
were gathered, being without an head as they are, &amp; euery one cleauing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his own priuate opinion, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can neuer all meete together, or if by anye power they were compelled therunto, they haue no means to agre in one, for that they wil not yeeld to any iudgement, but what is framed of their own braine, &amp; therefore it muſt needs be amongſt them, as we ſee it to be, <hi>Quot homines, tot ſententiae;</hi> So many men, ſo many opinions. Laſtly I would haue you here to marke the dealing of heretiks, who play by generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they play by the ſcriptures, for they take &amp; leaue as they luſte, &amp; as beſt ſerueth their turne. There haue bin in all, general Councels 18. Al ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, allowed, &amp; confirmed by one &amp; the ſelfeſame autority, of which the <hi>Greeks</hi> receiue only 7. the <hi>Lutherans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Florent. ſeſſ. 5. &amp; 6. Magdebur cent. 8. cap 9. &amp; cent. 9. cap. 9.</note> the firſt 6. the <hi>Eutychians</hi> which are in <hi>Aſia</hi> onely the firſt 3. the <hi>Neſtorians</hi> which are yet in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> onely the firſt 2. the <hi>Trinitaries</hi> which are in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Poleland,</hi> receiue none at all: Beholde the libertie of your Goſpell.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="reason">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:13600:29"/>
            <head>THE X. REASON. Fathers.</head>
            <p>THE Catholike Romane Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is moſt plainely taught by all the auncient Fathers of the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third, fourth, fift, and ſixt hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares after Chriſt, and hath bin euer, (without al controuerſie) taught of the Fathers of euerie age ſince vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day. That religion did <hi>Dyony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Areopagita, Saint Paule</hi> his Scholler, ſo manifeſtly teach,<note place="margin">Cauſaeus dialogue. 5 &amp; 11.</note> as <hi>Cauſaeus</hi> a french Proteſtant called him for his labour, a doating old man, much like as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Luther</hi> had ſaid before him, that, <hi>Areopagita</hi> his vvorkes vvere like to dreames,<note place="margin">In Capt. Babilonica</note> and moſt pernicious. The ſame faith was taught of ſaint <hi>Ignatius, Clemens, Iustinus, Tertullian, Cyprian, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> and in one word all the auncient Fathers not one excepted. This is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plaine in that the Catholikes are put, &amp; compelled by the Proteſtants
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13600:29"/>
to defend, maintaine, and vpholde the credit, and authoritie of the ſaide Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for the Proteſtants rayle at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Catholiks defend them: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants refuſe theyr authoritie, the Catholikes hold it for good: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants will not be tried by them: the Catholikes appeale to theyr iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and to be briefe, the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts make no more account of them, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then they can wreſt them to ſerue their turne, then thy doe of <hi>Beuis</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> or of <hi>Adam Bell.</hi> And in naming the Proteſtants, I include all the Puritanes: for I am not ignorant how the ſaide Proteſtants are driuen by the ſaid Puritanes, to defende the Fathers, and alſo are called papiſts for theyr labour. And hereby it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that the Fathers are with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and neyther with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, nor Puritanes. And whether all thoſe auncients, being men of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent wittes, of continuall ſtudie, of wonderfull learning, feruent in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, holie in conuerſation, greatlie in Gods fauour, mightie in vvorking of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13600:30"/>
miracles, &amp; adorned with many ſuch like giftes, were more like to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Scriptures freſhly deliuered vnto them from the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (who alſo no doubt, taught their ſchollers the true ſenſe thereof, and they theirs, from one age to another,) or theſe late fooliſh, vnſtudied, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, prophane, and arrogant fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, be iudges your ſelues But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is no maruaile though the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants doe contemne, yea reuile the Fathers,<note place="margin">Luther in Capt. Bab. Cauſaeus, vbi ſupra. Centuriat. centur. 2. cap. 10. Caluin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. cap. 13 num. 29. Centur. 2. cap. 5. Cauſaeus dialog. 8. &amp; 11. &amp; 6 beza in act Apoſt. ca. 23.</note> in ſaying they taught thinges moſt like to dreames; <hi>they were doating oldmen; they had foule blemiſhes, and tolde trifling tales; they had weedes and dregges, blaſphemyes, and monsters: they were child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, dull, and destitute of God, &amp; babled they knew not what: they were bewitched of the Diuell, as damned as the Diuell, blaſphemers, naughty, wicked:</hi> for they who cannot endure certaine ſet times to faſt in, no meruaile though they reuile <hi>S. Baſil, S. Gregory, Nazianzene, S. Leo, S. Chriſostome,</hi> which wrote ſuch notable Sermons of Lent, and of other faſting dayes, then vſed as they are now in the Catholike
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13600:30"/>
Church. And they, who be giuen to Luſt, to Gluttonie, to Ambition, to Couetouſnes, and doe teach ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as neceſſarilie bringeth foorth ſuch fruites, muſt needes contemne <hi>S. Baſil, S. Chriſostome, S. Hierome,</hi> and <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> who haue written ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently of the Order, Rule, &amp; Vertues of Monkes. And generally whereas the Doctrine of the auncient Fathers is cleane contrarie to the Doctrine of Proteſtants, no meruaile though they be reiected by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they euer haue bin of Heretikes. And although <hi>Iwell</hi> in his Sermon at Paules Croſſe, moſt impudently challenged the Catholiks to bring any thing for certaine points of theyr Religion out of the Doctours of the firſt ſixe hundred yeares: yet <hi>Laurence Humfrey</hi> his pue fellowe,<note place="margin">Humfridus in vita Iw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elli.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that hee gaue, and graunted to the papiſts more than was meete, and vvas to himſelfe iniurious, &amp;c. and ſo hee confeſſed againſt his companion, that the FATHERS of the Primitiue Church were on the Papiſts ſide, and conſequently not on theirs. And yet
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13600:31"/>
becauſe they haue founde by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that to teach Doctrine contrary to the auncient Fathers, ſoundeth but badlie in the peoples eares, in theyr Sermons they gladlie now &amp; then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge the authoritie of ſome Doctor or Father, vvhen they can by anie meanes wring, or wreſt any peece of a ſentence ſo, as it may ſeeme to make for them And indeede hee vvho al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeth the Doctours moſt, is moſt prayſed of the audience, as you vvell know, which is a pittifull thing in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ridiculous in the Preacher, vvho cannot but know, (if he haue read any of them himſelfe) that the Fathers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vtterly that Doctrine which hee wreſteth them to confirme, and in the meane time the pore audience think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that they were of this new Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vvhoſe ſimplicitie therein is moſt pittifullie abuſed, by the Preacher.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="reason">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:13600:31"/>
            <head>THE XI. REASON. Triall of Trueth.</head>
            <p>IT is manifeſt by the Holye Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that it appertaineth to the Church to try &amp; to diſcerne ſpirits, as alſo to determine &amp; to decide doubts. And agreeably therunto ſhee hath in all ages maſtered, ouer-ruled, &amp; cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuated the vnderſtanding of euerye one, were hee neuer ſo wiſe, neuer ſo learned, or had he neuer ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary giftes, except he obſtinatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended an errour, which if he did, hee was condemned for an heretike, &amp; ſo came to nothing. The Chatholike Church, I ſaye, directed by the Holye Ghoſt, hath euer ſeparated from the trueth, all moales, all ſingular opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, al errours and corruptions in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie mans workes and writings, in ſuch ſorte as that eaſilie and ſecurelye eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one maie knowe the trueth. And certainelie the Proteſtantes although they ſaye that they giue no credite to the CHVRCH, but ſo farre forth as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13600:32"/>
they finde in their Scriptures, doe, &amp; can not otherwiſe but receaue the ſame Scriptures vppon the Catholike Romane Churches credit, &amp; alſo the three Creedes of the Apoſtles, of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> and of <hi>Nice,</hi> and ſome Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of beleefe, as, the Holy Ghoſt to proceed from both the Father &amp; the Sonne, &amp; yet as from one beginning, and many tearmes, as, Perſon, Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Conſubſtantiall, Sacraments, &amp;c. which none coulde euer haue inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but onely the Catholike Church. Neyther is it poſsible for any man to know whether this Bible, which is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongeſt Chriſtians, be the true word of God indeede, or ſome fained thing, but onely vppon the Catholike Romane Churches credit. And Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> confeſſeth plainely, that he would not beleeue the Ghoſpell, but that the authoritie of the Catholike Church moued him thereunto.<note place="margin">Con. Epiſt Manich. c. 5. lib. 2. de doct. Chr. cap. 8.</note> And by the ſame Churches authoritie hee was mooued to beleeue the bookes of <hi>Tobie, Iudith, Canticles, Wiſedome, Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticus, Machabees, &amp;c.</hi> as he himſelf ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerelie
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13600:32"/>
affirmeth. And ſurely it is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull to ſee, how the Church of God receauing the Olde Teſtament from the Iewes, and manifeſting to the world the Canon of the Holy bookes of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, hath in al times, in ſo many alterations, and chaunges, kept from the deſtruction, &amp; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Heretikes, Iewes, and Panims the whole authenticall corps of Holy Scripture, in ſuch maner, as no Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike in the world can charge her with adding, or diminiſhing the leaſt iote thereof. Iudge you here whether the madnes of theſe new fellowes, be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be wondred at, or no, who doe credit and beleeue the Church in this point, and will not doe the ſame in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Why ſhould they rather truſt the Church in this, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in other things. And I would euery man would here conſider the wonderfull integritie of the Catholike Romane Church, in keeping the Holy Bible ſo entire, and vncorrupted theſe fifteene hundred yeares together at the leaſt, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſticall treacherie of theſe of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13600:33"/>
the new Religion, who occupying no Bible, nor hauing to doe with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures for a thouſand yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather (as they themſelues confeſſe) haue after the vniuſt vvreſting it out of the handes of the iuſt poſſeſſors thereof, robbed the Church of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whole bookes, &amp; beſides of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie partes, and particles of the ſame. What theſe fellowes would bring the Holy Bible vnto in time, if they ſhuld hold on, they may eaſily geſſe, vvho know their manifold corruption ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in ſo few yeares. And yet forſooth, they vvill haue all controuerſies to be tried by only ſcriptures; which if they were not by them corrupted, &amp; falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie tranſlated, yet could theye neuer finde out any ſecure truth by them only, for that none of them alloweth anie other mans expoſition but his owne, and in ſo dealing they can but haue a geſſe, or an opinion, or fantaſie, but no faith at all. Which thing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare more plainely; I aske the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant how he relying vpon only ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, can ſhew mee certainely vvhich
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13600:33"/>
bookes be Scripture, and which not? And if hee be vnlearned, how know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hee that the tranſlation which hee vſeth is truely made out of <hi>Hebrew, Greeke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Latine?</hi> And then how is hee ſure of the ſence, &amp; expoſition? And if he be neuer ſo learned, &amp; haue neuer ſo many helps, all that hee can ſearch and finde out, is but a priuate mans o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and conſequentlie, his Faith which hee ſeemeth to haue, is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon his owne particular iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo indeed is no faith at all, but an opinion onely, as I ſaid before: for faith muſt haue Gods expreſſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie for her foundation. Here you may conſider the miſerable ſtate, and condition of your newe Ghoſpellers: in that forſaking the Catholike and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall faith of Chriſtendome, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the vniuerſal Church, as founded vppon Scripture (vvhich Church Chriſt and his Apoſtles gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expreſſe Commiſsion to beleeue) which was properly Faith, &amp; founded vpon a rocke which could not faile; in that forſaking (I ſay) that fortres, they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13600:34"/>
caſt themſelues into the waues of new opinions, whereby they haue no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie at all, but euery one chuſeth vvhat hee liketh to himſelfe, vvhich choiſe is properly called Hereſie, and ſo the word ſignifieth. And let anie Proteſtant in our Countrie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land tell mee, why he doth rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue his owne iudgement in points of Religion, then the iudgement of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Caluin,</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> whome he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth were ſo excellent men? for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that hath any learning know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that they taught otherwiſe then now is taught in England. This you may plainely ſee the only touchſtone of truth, to be the Catholike Church, which cannot faile, and that they who cleaue to her iudgement, haue moſt vndoubtedly the truth; whereas on the other ſide, they, who ground only vpon Scriptures, expounding them according to their owne fantaſie, and braine, playing the Maiſters, and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, and Boat-ſwaines themſelues, &amp; admitting no iudge, no interpreter, no antiquitie, nor any other manner
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13600:34"/>
of tryall, (which is the greateſt mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and malediction that can be) muſt needes be deſtitute of all cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, and of all Religion, and of all ſtay, and of all foundation, and of all rule, and of all order, and muſt needes wrangle and iangle without end, and without meanes to make an end, and muſt needes cauſe Nouelties without number, and libertie of life without feare or force of Eccleſiaſticall Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline to reſtraine them; and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, they haue no meanes to reſt, vntill the end in Atheiſme.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="reason">
            <head>THE XII. REASON. The vſe and custome of the Church.</head>
            <p>THE vſe, cuſtome, and practiſe of the Church, hath (as it vvas in the prime thereof.) beene alvvaies an infallible rule to direct and order thinges by.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:13600:35"/>This the Apoſtle, after manie argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to prooue that women ſhould not be beareheaded in Churches, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed as a Fort moſt ſtronge, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible to beare downe the gain-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof: <hi>If any man</hi> (ſaith hee, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding mine argumentes) <hi>doe ſeeme to be contentious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> 
               <hi>we haue no ſuch cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> (as women to pray vncouered) <hi>nor the Church of God.</hi> And agreeablie vnto this Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith: <hi>If the whole Church throughout the world doe vſe any thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 118. cap. 5.</note> 
               <hi>onely to call in question, wheather that thing ſhould be ſo done, is a point of moſt proude, or moſt ſtraunge madneſſe.</hi> And for this cauſe againſt the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> hee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth ordinarilie out of the Churches cuſtome, proouing Children to be borne in ſinne,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 105.</note> becauſe the Church doth Baptize them for Remiſsion of ſinnes. And becauſe the Church v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to Exorciſe them, and to blowe vpon them, therefore the Diuell hath power ouer them, and that by ſinne. And to this ſaith hee, <hi>the</hi> Pelagians <hi>with all theyr crafte coulde not anſwere:</hi> for they durſt not ſay, (as the Proteſtants
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13600:35"/>
ſay) <hi>wee care not for the Churches cuſtome, wee weigh not thereof.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De bono perſeu. ca. 23.</note> Manie ſuch like argumentes hath the ſame Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustne</hi> elſe vvhere: But in few vvordes the cuſtome of the church was a thing ſo vndoubted, as neuer any Heretike before this our age durſt aduenture to ſtand againſt the ſame altogether: But Hereſies euer conſiſted only in ſome matter of erronious iudgement, and falſe opinion, but the teachers thereof neuer went about to chaunge the face of Religion, as to take away the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Church, as the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants are bold to doe. And ſurelie in this point the malepeartneſſe, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate boldneſſe of the new Ghoſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers is wonderfull, who durſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attempt to chaunge diuers pointes of the Churches vſe, &amp; practiſe, which in all ages, of all men, was accounted ſo heinous an offence to doe, but alſo made no bones to take all quite away, Cuſtomes, Ceremonies, Orders, yea and the <hi>Holie Maſſe</hi> it ſelfe, placing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteede thereof in ſome places Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Pſalmes ill tranſlated into the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13600:36"/>
Vulgar tongue, &amp; in ſome other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Ballades made of Pſalmes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie called <hi>Geneua</hi> Pſalmes, vvith rayling Sermons, and in other places other ſtuffe, as beſt pleaſed the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of the deuiſers thereof. And to theſe new inuentions (forſooth) muſt the common people be compelled to come, and to forſake &amp; renounce the Seruice and Sacrifice of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, left by God Almightie, and continued euer through out all Generations, as it muſt doe (manger all Proteſtants heades) euen vnto the worlds end.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="reason">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:13600:36"/>
            <head>THE XIII. REASON. Doctrine.</head>
            <p>THAT Church vvhoſe Doctrine tendeth to Mortification, and Holineſſe of life muſt needes be the true Church, and conſequentlie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by Gods holie Spirit; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, that Sect or Congregation, which teacheth the contrarie, is moſt vndoubtedly falſe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie guided by an euill ſpirit.</p>
            <p>This is ſo manifeſt, as it needeth no proofe: for euery man knoweth that the Catholike Church is called Holy, becauſe it profeſſeth or teacheth, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that which is Holie. Now if a man conſider duelie the Doctrine of the Romane Church, he ſhall finde it to be of the former ſort, and eaſilie he may perceaue the Doctrine of this new religion to be of the latter. But I vvill not heere ſpeake of the fruites of CATHOLIKES, and Proteſtants,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13600:37"/>
(although indeede there be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon in life, for that euery one ſeeth and eaſilie confeſſeth the Catholikes to liue moſt vprightlie, &amp; Saint-like) but I ſpeake of that which their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on teacheth them to doe: for of that eſpecially our Lord meant vvhen he ſaid:<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> 
               <hi>You ſhall know them by theyr fruites.</hi> Firſt, therefore to declare this pointe, if you compare the clergie of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Religion, vvith theſe new Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie men, you may ſee the Orders, and Inſtitutions of the one ſorte to mooue them to mortification, &amp; to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of earthly things, and the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the other to prick them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to all vanitie, &amp; to carnall liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: for a Prieſt of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> receaueth in a moſt ſolemne manner ſeauen Orders, whereof three are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Holie, becauſe they are about Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and holie thinges, as the Body &amp; Blood of our Sauiour, holy veſſels, &amp;c And euery thing which the ſaid prieſt muſt vſe, is holy, and therefore there is required in him the greateſt puritie poſsiblie to be had, ſo as he muſt haue
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13600:37"/>
and thoughts free from all carnallitie, and worldly thinges, and for ſuch like cauſes he is reſtrained from marriage, although it be in it ſelfe honorable, &amp; inſtituted by God himſelfe, but yet who ſo is yoaked therein muſt needes apply himſelfe to worldly affaires, and ſo is diuided as the Apoſtle ſaith.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> And becauſe he is reſtrained from marriage &amp; bound to liue Chaſte or continent, hee may not vſe anye trimming, or tricking vp of himſelfe in amorous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre, nor vſe any dalliance, or fondnes with weomen, but euer remembring that he is as a dead man, in regarde of ſuch thinges, he muſt be far from ſuch lightneſſe, but on the other ſide, the Proteſtant Miniſter hauing receiued no Orders, but a certaine kinde of Deaconſhippe, and Miniſterſhippe, of their owne inuention, and hauing no Holy or Sacred thinges to deale with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, but left to all liberty of winning &amp; rewinning, which he cannot ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe without woing, woe he cannot handſomely, without hee ſomething tricke &amp; trimme vp himſelfe to allure,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13600:38"/>
&amp; pleaſe the eie of his ſweet hart, muſt needes goe trickly with faire ſtarched ruffes, fine mouſaches, trimme tuſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians, vſe amorous glaunces, yea &amp; that ſometimes when they are reading their Chapters in the Church, with a thowſand ſuch-like fonde &amp; fooliſhe inconueniences, which enſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. Furthermore, the Romane Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion teacheth Reſtitution of goods wrongfully taken, and of all wronges whatſoeuer, which brideleth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth people from bribery, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, theft, vſury, ſymony, &amp; from ſuch like: But the Proteſtants medling litle with ſuch doctrine, leaueth al at large to his folowers, without reſtraint of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch crime. The Catholike religion teacheth obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vowes &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes which muſt needes cauſe great truſt &amp; fidelity in the profeſſors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the Proteſtant teacheth, that they bind not in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, which openeth the doare to diſtruſt, and maketh the people that one wil not truſt another, but muſt haue him in bandes, with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erties &amp; with all faſtnes poſſible to be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13600:38"/>
deuiſed. The Catholike religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; faſting, which mortifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth our bodies, &amp; enricheth our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teacheth to eat fleſh &amp; al kinds of meats euery day, as often as the belly deſireth, which cauſeth plenty of luſt in the carcaſe, &amp; dearth &amp; ſcarcity in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth. The Catholike Religion forbiddeth Land-Lords to raiſe their rents, except vrge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t occaſion driue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to doe, by which prohibition infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of people be benefited &amp; holpe, the Proteſtant teaching the Land-Lord to doe what he liſt with his owne, ruyneth, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly beggereth thowſandes of poore people. The Catholike religion teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Marriage, to bee indiſſoluble, ſo as they who be once lawefully Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, can neuer be ſo diuorſed, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partye maie euer Marry againe, whileſt the other liueth, which cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Man and Wife to beare much one with the other, knowing there is noe hope of chaunging, but the Proteſtant teaching that they may Marry again, yeeldeth them occaſion, one eaſilie
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13600:39"/>
to diſlike of the other, beeing both in hope to marry againe, and to chainge as ofte as they liſte. The Catholike religion teacheth that al Laws of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, which bee not expreſlye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the word of God, doe bind the ſubiects in conſcience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to obay them, not onely openly, but alſo in ſecret, whereupon doe followe peace, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and obedience to Superiours, but the Proteſtant teaching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, bringeth Magiſtrates into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte, and cauſeth al diſorder in the Common-wealth. The Catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion teacheth differences of ſinnes, ſome to be more grieuous than others, ſome Mortall, ſome Veniall, and that Concupiſcence or naturall inclination to luſt of it ſelfe is no ſinne, whereupon Catholikes are taught to ſtriue againſt this motion, knowing it to be no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence except they yeelde vnto it, and alſo they manfully fight againſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinnes, although they cannot eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auoide leſſer, or Veniall offences: but the Proteſtant teaching, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinne, be it neuer ſo ſmall doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13600:39"/>
damnation, and Concupiſcence to be ſinne, which no man can auoid, maketh people, to leaue all to God his mercy, but neuer to reſiſte ſin, nor motion thereunto, for that in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion it is but loſt labour ſo to do. The Catholike Religion teaceth, rewarde of good and bad life in the worlde to come, which cauſeth people to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to doe al good workes, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide all euill as farre forth as poſſibly they can: but the Proteſtant teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the contrary, giueth the people occaſion to be negligent in dooing of good, and little or nothing fearfull to doe euill. The Catholike Religion teacheth Confeſſion to a Prieſt of all deadly ſins which we can remember, vnder paine of damnation, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth people from ſinne, &amp; cauſeth them particularly to be wel inſtructed and counſeled: but the Proteſtant ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that away, ſetteth open a doare to all wickedneſſe, and to loſeneſſe of life, as alſo to ignorance. The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion teacheth Satisfaction to be donne either in this life, or in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13600:40"/>
in the next, which cauſeth people to vndertake willingly penal works, as faſting, praier, almeſe-deeds, &amp;c. &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſideration of this, &amp; of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde in Heauen, they builded ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny goodly Churches, Colledges, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, Hoſpitalles, Schooles, &amp;c. they gaue ſuch large Almes, they pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed their bodies with Faſting and wearing of hair-cloath, they watched, they praied, they Married pore &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe children, &amp; did a thowſande kinds of ſuch like good works: but the Proteſtant denying Satisfaction, and taking away Purgatorye, robbeth the pore of their Almes, children of their education, the ſicke of their releefe, &amp; maketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnwilling to doe any good worke at all. The Catholike Religion teacheth Free-wil, which cauſeth peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to endeuour to doe good, &amp; to flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euil: the Proteſtant taking it away, diſcourageth men vtterly from doing good workes, for who will goe about a thing which is not in his power, or for the which, if he did it, he ſhall haue no recompence. The Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13600:40"/>
teacheth the holy Maſſe, to be a Sacrifice in which the very Body and Bloode of our Sauiour is offered vp, which maketh people ſo deuout, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent at the ſeruice thereof, as that they kneele altogether, pray continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, giue atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance to no other thing for that time, &amp; therupon it commeth that they beare ſuch reſpecte &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Prieſtes: but the Proteſtant, allowing nothing but certaine chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, pſalmes: and collects, to be read in the vulgar toung, giueth the people occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be vndeuout, irreligious, &amp; vnreuerent for that they ſee nothing worthie of reuerence. Heereupon you may ſee the people at the Proteſtants ſeruice, ſome ſtaring about them, with out Boke or Bead in their hands, ſome walking, ſome talking, ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>angling, but none kneeling, or praying, or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any reuerence at al, either to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, or to miniſter, &amp; no maruel when euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he can but read, can play the miniſter at home as wel as the beſt curate of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al. Many ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of doctrine might be ſet down,
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:13600:41"/>
are the publiſhers, and maintainers, &amp; Heretikes &amp; Proteſtants the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and denyers thereof: for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike affirmeth Baptiſme of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be neceſſarie, the Proteſtant deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it. The Catholike affirmeth men to be iuſtified by inherent iuſtice, the Proteſtant denyeth it. The Catholike affirmeth certaine preparations to be neceſſarie to iuſtification on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the proteſtant denyeth it. The Catholike affirmeth good works to be neceſſarie, and to haue theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the Proteſtant denieth it. The Catholike affirmeth that we haue free vvill, the Proteſtant denieth it. The Catholike affirmeth that vvee may keepe the Commaundementes, the Proteſtant denyeth it. The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like affirmeth humane Lawes agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to GODS WORD to bynde in conſcience, the Proteſtant denyeth it. The Catholicke affirmeth ſeauen SACRAMENTS, the Proteſtant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth fiue, if not all. The Catholike affirmeth Prieſt-hoode, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant denyeth it. The Catholicke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13600:41"/>
ſingle life of the Cleargie, the Proteſtant denyeth it. The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke affirmeth Pennance, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant denyeth it. The Catholicke affirmeth Contrition, the Proteſtant denyeth it. The Catholicke affirmeth Confeſsion, Satisfaction, Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Prayer for the deade, Exequyes, Anniuerſaries, the Proteſtant deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them all. The Catholicke affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Reall Preſence, the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the holie Maſſe, Aultars, and all thinges belonging thereunto, the Proteſtant denyeth them all. The Catholicke affirmeth vvorſhipping of Saintes, prayer vnto them, feaſtes of them, adoration of theyr Riliques, and Images, the Proteſtant denyeth all. The Catholicke affirmeth trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vpp of Churches, Ceremonies, Singing, Pilgrimages, Supremacie of Saint <hi>Peeter,</hi> Monaſticall vowes, choyce of meats and faſting, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant denyeth all. The Catholicke affirmeth all the Bible to be Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Scripture, the Proteſtant denyeth diuers partes thereof. The Catholike
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13600:42"/>
affirmeth the perpetuall virginitie of our bleſſed Lady, the Proteſtant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth it. The Catholike affirmeth the Church to be viſible, the Proteſtant denyeth it. And many moe ſuch like pointes of Chriſtian Doctrine the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church deliuereth to her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as ſhe hath receaued them from her Spouſe Chriſt, which the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant vtterlie denieth, and indeede af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, or putteth downe nothing more then he found before in the ſaid Catholike Church: wherby you may ſee their Doctrine to be altogeather nothing, but meere negations, &amp; flatt denyals; and ſo I ſee plainely that by their Negatiue Doctrine they haue profited the Chriſtian world nothing at all, but haue taken away from it much of that which it had; and in this manner as they are, any horſe, or aſſe, if he could but ſpeake as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe did, ſo it were but one worde, that is, <hi>Nego,</hi> might be as good a Proteſtant as the beſt of them all. Neyther can it be ſaide, that they doe as the firſte Chriſtians did, which denyed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13600:42"/>
the falſe and ſuperſtitious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the Heathens: for that the Chriſtians did that by manifeſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion from God himſelfe, by work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Miracles &amp; by planting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion in place thereof: but the Proteſtantes neither doe that which they do, by any authoritie from God, nor euer could work any one miracle, as is afore-ſaide, and inſteede of that which they reiect &amp; pull downe, they place iuſt nothing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="reason">
            <head>THE XV. REASON. Diuinitie.</head>
            <p>IF you looke into the Vniuerſities of the Catholiks, &amp; of Proteſtants, you ſhal ſee in the one the whole corps of Diuinitie, and of Chriſtian trueth moſt pythelie and profoundly taught: but in the other nothing but a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of pelting obiections taken out of <hi>Caluins</hi> Inſtitutions, or out of the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deburgenſes,</hi> or out of ſome Hereticall Pamphlet, together with wreſted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13600:43"/>
of the new Teſtament, which they haue learned of <hi>Beza,</hi> or of ſome ſuch like fellow, &amp; in ſome they trouble themſelues with nothing, but onely with the Controuerſies of this time, &amp; that is all the Diuinity which they haue, or meddle withall. But the Catholike Diuines ſtudie, and teache in theyr Schooles moſt exactlie, all thinges vvhich man may in this life know of God ALMIGHTIE, <hi>of his Simplicitie, Perfection, Goodneſſe, Infinitie, of his being in his creatures, of his immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, Eternitie, Vnitie, knowledge, and ſeeing of him, of his names, Science, Idees, Life, Will, Loue, Iustice, and Mercie, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, Power, Felicitie, of the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt, of theyr Equalitie, Vnitie, Conſubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in one</hi> GOD-HEADE, <hi>of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thinges, of Angels, of theyr ſubſtance, Incorporcitie, locall motion, Knowledge, Will, Loue, Production, Goodneſſe, and Badneſſe, of mans Creation, of his Bodie, Soule, of all the powers, and parts thereof, of his Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the end whereunto hee is created, of Vertue, and Vice in generall, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13600:43"/>
of the Incarnation of Gods Sonne, ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two moſt different natures of God, and Man, both entire, both complete, without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtion, or confuſion into the vnitie of one perſon, of the perfections &amp; defects aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, of the Reſurrection &amp; Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> and of many other profound pointes, vvhich the Proteſtantes neuer beate their braines about, and indeede they cannot poſsiblie ſtudie theſe thinges throughlie, beeing ſomuch occupied about wooing, vvenching, and wiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, taking vppon them to be Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of Diuinitie, and Husbandes alſo.</p>
            <p>And therefore if the learnedſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them ſhould appeare in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Schooles, or Vniuerſities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, hee would not once dare to open his mouth in matters of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, among the great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of moſt excellent learned men, which there are founde, as wee haue vvell proued by ſuch of your Proteſtants as nowe and then goe abroade to forraine V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIVERSITIES, and are very quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie brought to Confeſſe theyr ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13600:44"/>
in this kinde, for that they ſcarce vnderſtand the verie ordinarie tearmes of the learned ſciences, which the others doe fullie poſſeſſe. And I pray you, what a learned Clargie was there in Queene <hi>Maryes</hi> time in our Countrie of England, in reſpect of theſe pore creatures, that occupy now theyr Prebends, and ſit in the ſunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of theyr new pretended Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell with theyr Wiues and Children rounde about them? Were not one <hi>Tonstall,</hi> one <hi>Watſon,</hi> one <hi>Christopherſon,</hi> for learning, one <hi>Feckna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> one <hi>Gardener,</hi> one <hi>White,</hi> for wiſdome &amp; learning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, able to ſet to Schoole all your ruffed Cleargie at this day, for tearme of life, and after, as by their workes &amp; writings yet extant doth wel appeare. This groſſe ignorance of theſe newe Ghoſpellers is the cauſe that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doe remaine vtterly voide of the knowledge of myſteries, which they are bound to beleeue vppon paine of damnation, and they cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be, when as their Leaders &amp; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours are altogether vnskilfull of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13600:44"/>
points afore-named: But if they can ſpeake a litle Greeke, and a few words in Hebrew, and vſe ſome Inke horne Eloquence, with rayling againſt Pope and Papiſtes, then are they forſooth deepe Diuines. Take the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctour of them all, and ſet him to reaſon with an Heathen, or with an Atheiſt, and you ſhall ſee what good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arguments hee will make, nay you ſhall ſee him betray the truth for lack of learning, for that he is vtterly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (as they are all) of Schoole Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. And hereupon it is that theyr Preachers comming to reaſon vvith the Turkiſh Prieſtes haue beene dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to yeelde, and haue become Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans: for indeed one who taketh vpon him to be Doctor of Diuinitie, ought to be ſo inſtructed &amp; furniſhed with Philoſophie, Morall, Phyſicall, and Metaphyſicall, with Logicke, and with all humane helps, with Councels, Fathers, Hiſtories, and ſuch like, and not only with the bare text of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as that he may be able to defend the faith of Chriſt in all points, againſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13600:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Iewes, Turkes, Heathens, Atheiſtes,</hi> &amp; not only againſt heretiks. And here I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but admire the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of God towards his Church, in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing it with all kinds of learning, &amp; ſciences, whereby it may defend, and maintaine it ſelf againſt all ſorts of eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, be they <hi>Iewes, Turks, Heathens, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theists</hi> or <hi>Heretikes</hi> vvhatſoeuer: for in the Vniuerſities thereof, you may ſee moſt learnedly, ſubſtantially, orderly, and vniuerſallie taught all Chriſtian truth, and that in ſhort ſpace: for in 4. or 5. yeares the whole courſe of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is taught vnder two or three rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp; in the ſame time the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies by another reader, by another all the new Teſtament is learnedlie, &amp; foundly expounded, beſides an 100. publike Diſputations euerie yeare of ſome whole matter, as of Baptiſme, of the Euchariſt, of the Trinitie, of the Incarnation, of Angels, of the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, &amp;c. and withall, the whole Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble read ouer at Table euery yeare, &amp; alwaies after Dinner and Supper, two Chapters of it, one of the new, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13600:45"/>
of the old teſtament diligentlie examined, vvith familiar conference betweene the learned, and the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſort. And beſides all this there are taught <hi>Caſes of Conſcience,</hi> in which is ſet downe, what is ſinne, and vvhat not: the differences of ſinnes, which great, which leſſer, &amp;c. which is a moſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; a moſt profitable kind of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and therefore is much ſtudied, and practiſed by Catholike Prieſts, &amp; Diuines, who teach the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to rule, and to order their liues and actions. Neyther doth the Proteſtant meddle with theſe matters of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but fraighteth his ſhip only with Faith, and neuer beateth his braine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſinnes, for that he thinketh none to be imputed to ſuch Predeſtinated, as they all weene them-ſelues to be, vvhich cauſeth the people theyr fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers to be vtterly ignorant of the nature, differences, and quality of ſins, and conſequently nothing fearefull, or ſtayed by any conſcience to committ the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="reason">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:13600:46"/>
            <head>THE XVI. REASON. Holineſſe of Life.</head>
            <p>ALthough vpon externall &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde holineſſe vve may not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly inferre true Religion, for that among Iewes, Turkes, and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelles, ſome make great ſhewe of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and deuotion, yet we may truelie argue that amongſt what company or congregation ſoeuer, there is not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, any piety, deuotion, mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or holineſſe of life, but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-wiſe, impiety, irreligioſity, carnalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and loſeneſſe of life, vniuerſally to be ſeene, and that neceſſarily iſſuing out of the bowelles of their doctrine, that there poſſibly can be no true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: For that the ſpirit of God, who guideth, directeth, and as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth true Religion, will not ſuffer it to be vniuerſally fruitleſſe, and of no efficaſie: For otherwiſe it ſhould be fruſtrated of it end, which is to make the embracers thereof Holy, &amp; good.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13600:46"/>
And beſides it was foretolde by the Prophet,<note place="margin">Eſa. cap. 11</note> that CHRIST his Doctrine ſhould alter mens conditions, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſo as ſuch as were moſt fierce, ſauage, and wicked before, ſhould by it become moſt humble, kind, &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, which can no way be applied to the Proteſtants, as their bloody trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies raiſed in <hi>Fraunce, Flaunders, Scotland Switzerland,</hi> and in other partes of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> ſufficiently doe witneſſe, where were ſlaine aboue an hundred thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande people within one yeere, by the rebellion and wars of the countrieme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt their Lords for the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of Religion, ſuch humility,<note place="margin">Sledan.</note> obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and meekeneſſe of hart, this new Doctrine imprinted preſentlye as it came. And albeit externall holineſſe doth not (as is aforeſaide) neceſſarilie inferre true religion, yet doth it giue a great preſumption thereof, eſpecially if there be inwarde zeale, and aboue all, Charity. Nowe it cannot be but moſt plaine to euery one, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both, that the liues of Catholikes, in all landes, and that in all ages, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13600:47"/>
namely of our aunceſtours, and prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours there in <hi>Englande</hi> were, &amp; are of thoſe who now be, for the moſt part moſt Holy, moſt Innocent, moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and moſt Godly: and the liues of the Proteſtantes ordinarilye moſt lewde, looſe, and voide of piety. And firſt, if you take a viewe of the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, &amp; of the Religious-men, &amp; weo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Catholike church, you ſhal finde infinit numbers to haue lead Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall and Angelicall liues heere on earth, free from all worldly, carnall, &amp; earthly deſires, with contempt of all humane &amp; tranſitory things, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> the firſt Eremite, S. <hi>Anthony, S. Hilarion, S. Greg. S. Ier. S. Aug. S. Bern. S. Fraun. S. Dom. S, Bened. S. Thom. Aquinas, S. Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture,</hi> with innumerable others ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, whoſe liues were moſt heauenly, togeather with millions of profeſſed Virgins, vowed Widdowes, poore by wil and promiſe, perſons of both ſexes dedicated to God by renouncing the vvorlde with the delightes thereof, ſome liuing in Deſerts, or Caues of the earth, ſome in Cloyſters in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13600:47"/>
vnder obedience; with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite numbers of ſecular Prieſtes, moſt godlie and deuoute. And although I will not denie, but that ſome there were among the Cleargie, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people in this latter age, which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not according to theyr Orders, &amp; Rules, but ſcandalized the Church of God: yet may I truelie ſay, that they who did ſo, vvere not the hundreth part ſo many, as the Proteſtantes moſt falſely make them: But the trueth is, that among a great number (for there were of Prieſtes and Religious men, at the leaſt fiue times ſo many, as there be now miniſters) a few were bad, and now the miniſters being but fewe in reſpect of them, are all naught. And no meruaile: for the Catholike Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, and Religious perſons, were by theyr Orders bound to ſundrie &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers houres of prayer, as to ſeauen in the day &amp; night, the religious to riſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery night at midnight, to pray &amp; ſing laudes to God, when others ſleep two or three houres togeather, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Exerciſes, Contemplations, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13600:48"/>
Meditations in the day time, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue ſo much as one vvhole houre voyde of ſome godlie employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. I would you did but ſee the manner of the liues of the bleſſed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucynes, which here to recount would be ſo long, and hardlie could I reckon vp all theyr holy Exerciſes of mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, or of the happie Fathers of the Societie of Ieſus, or of others ſuch like. Oh what Faſting, what Prayer, vvhat Meditation, what Contemplation, what wearing of Haire-cloth, what whiping, of themſelues, what watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what viſiting of the ſicke, what teaching of the ignoraunt, vvhat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking of Sinners, vvhat comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the afflicted ſhoulde you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde? Theſe pray, whileſt your mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters playe: Theſe taſte, whileſt they feaſte: Theſe meditate the Contempt of the World, whileſt they beat their braines, to compaſſe worldly commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities: Theſe Watche &amp; ſing Praiſes to God in the Night, whileſt they in a warme bedde hugge their <hi>Sweete heart in their armes.</hi> Who is he amongeſt you
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13600:48"/>
which ſeeth not, and is not aſhamed of the liues of your miniſters? Are not ſome of them almoſt in euery circuite hanged for robberies, for rapes, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned for Zodomie, for hauing diuers wiues at once, for debt, and for other knaueries. The law bindeth them to haue but one Wife at once, and ſhee muſt bee vewed by two Iuſtices of Peace, to ſee that ſhee be a maide for ſooth. But doe they not now &amp; then take their wiues from <hi>Colmans</hi> hedge,<note place="margin">Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence had the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car of wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ram his trul by his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> and ſome, other common ſtrumpets? and doe not theyr wiues proue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after? An hundred examples I could here alleadge to prooue theſe thinges, but I will not pollute my paper at this time with ſuch filthie matter. Looke into the Laitie of the Proteſtants, and tell mee weather there euer was ſuch Pride, eſpecially in apparell? Did not all theſe new-faſhioned attyres, come in with your new religion? Your looſe Gownes, your Traines, your Verdin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales, your Borders, your Peringles, your Coronets, your Wyres, your Ruffes ſtarched, white, blew, &amp;c. your
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:13600:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Shew me whome this Ghoſpell hath made of a rauenous glutton, a ſober abstainer: of cruell gentle: of couetous, liberall: of a ſlaunderer, a good reporter: of an vnchaſte ſinner, a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous liuer. I will ſhew thee many that haue bin made worſe then them-ſelues.</hi> Thus far <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> And no meruaile though the followers be ſuch, when as theyr verie firſt Apoſtle, Ringleader, and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of all, who firſt broake the ice, &amp; was indeed the Authour, and founder of theyr Religion, led a moſt brutiſhe life: for was he not a leacherous Friar? tooke he not a Nunne to Wife, if ſo I may tearme it? An act not onlie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by holie writ, but by the Ciuil Lawes,<note place="margin">L. Si quis non dica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. cap. de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Cop. &amp; cleric.</note> and by <hi>Iouinian</hi> the Emperour aboue a thouſand yeres agoe, and that vnder the paine of death. Surpaſſed he not all other in Pride? Confeſſeth hee not that hee had conference with the diuell about the Maſſe? Was not Enuie and Couetouſnes the cauſes of his reuolt? Read his life, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee was a man fit to Reforme the Chriſtian Worlde, or rather ſent to ſhame all his followers? Good Lord,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13600:49"/>
that men can be ſo blinde, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched, as to thinke that the trueth from Heauen ſhould be reuealed to ſuch a one; or that ſuch ſhould haue grace to know the trueth, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, who neuer faſt, ſeldome, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer praie to obtaine the ſame, neuer puniſh theyr bodies, neuer mortifie theyr earthlie members, &amp;c. rather then to a number of quiet, modeſt, &amp; harmeles men, who by prayer, by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, by almeſ deedes, by workes of mercie, by all vertuous meanes labour to attaine the knowledge of the truth. And who is he that can deny, but that in our aunceſtors dayes when Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion flouriſhed, brauerie in apparrell was vnknowne, and inſteede thereof innocent plaineneſſe vvas to be ſeene, &amp; that there was no chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, no new deuiſes, litle lawing, for when anie ſtrife fell out, the Prieſt theyr Ghoſtlie Father decided the matter, and made them friends; ſeldome any ſingle woman miſcarried in any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, no Simony, no Vſury, litle fraude or deceit, each one truſted other with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13600:50"/>
bill or bond, and to be briefe, that euery where raigned ſimplicity, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency? Oh how many thouſandes then left the world before it left the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dedicating themſelues whollie to the ſeruice of God, and that of all Eſtates: many Kings and Queenes not only of other Countries, but diuers euen of England, gaue ouer their Kingdomes and became Religious men, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. And the like did innumerable of inferiour degrees: whereas the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants prouide by waſt, deſolation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and (as it were) by law, that no ſuch orders of holie men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men be amongſt them: they will haue no Maides, but ſuch as can get no matches, no man is poore amongſt them but vvith grudge, and much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his wil, no vow is made to God, but if it ſhould be, it muſt not be kept, faſters with them are Phariſes, Monks mad men, &amp; thoſe which mortifie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they account Hypocrites, &amp; in in one word they are in theyr liues, as they be in doctrine, Libertines. And in nothing more doth the difference
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13600:50"/>
of the efficacy of their doctrine, &amp; the Catholikes appeare then in this; that if for feare of troubles, or for any other cauſe, one who was a Cath. is become in outward ſhow a Proteſtant (for in his conſcience ſuch a one ſeldome or neuer thinketh the Proteſtants religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be true) the ſame is ſo far from bettering his former life thereby, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his ſaying before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged) as that you may ſee him wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe in al kind of ſins. Set before your eies any one ther in <hi>England,</hi> who hath left the Catholike Religion, &amp; is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Proteſtant, &amp; marke whether he be not as a you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g calfe let out of his crew, or as a colt leapt out of his inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? How manie may you ſee there amongſt you of ſuch good fellowes, which ſhew plainely that they haue, <hi>Conſcientiam cauteriatam, a ſeared Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> If you turne any Seminary Prieſt to your ſide, doth he liue more vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tedly with you, then hee liued before in his own profeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or doth he not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then drinke vp any kind of ſinne as eaſilie as a Dogge lapeth water?
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13600:51"/>
But on the other ſide, if anie doe leaue the Proteſtants, &amp; become a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, doth he not forthwith leaue al his vices? I wiſh you would but conſider a litle the wonderfull chaunge of ſuch a one, whom I may more eaſilie leaue to your conſideration, then deſcribe him: but ſurely if you did ſee into it, you would ſay: <hi>Digitus Dei eſt hic, this is the finger, or power of God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="reason">
            <head>THE XVII. REASON. Constancie in Doctrine.</head>
            <p>THE Doctrine of the Romaine Church hath euer remained ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and ſtated without chaunge or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation, howſoeuer time euer fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, altereth many thinges to diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, and no man will denie but that it had the truth, when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſaid to the Romanes:<note place="margin">Rom. ca. 1.</note> 
               <hi>I giue thanks to my God through Ieſus Chriſt for you all, becauſe your faith is reported in the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall world.</hi> Therefore vntil it be ſhewed
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13600:51"/>
that it hath ſwarued from that Faith vvhich the Apoſtle then ſpoke of, I cannot but iudge it to haue the true Religion. And I thinke that no man can proue, that euer anie Pope, or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe in anye See did at anye time chaunge in any point the Religion of his predeceſſour. For example ſake, if you looke but into the See of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> in your owne Countrye, &amp; rekon from him who was Arch-biſhop ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in King Henry the eight his daies, before he chaunged Religion, you ſhal find that that Arch-biſhop taught the ſame Religion in all pointes, which his next predeceſſor had do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e before him, and he the ſame that his next prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, and ſo from one to another e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vntil the firſt that ſate in that See. The very ſame may you ſee in other Biſhops Sees, and eſpecially in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike See, the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> able to proue that the ſucceſſor at any time changed the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of his predeceſſour, &amp; ſo it muſt needes be al one &amp; the ſame that was immediately before this new religion,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13600:52"/>
and at the firſt beginning, or in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time. For I aſke the proteſtants (for examples ſake) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Italy, Fraunce,</hi> or <hi>Spaine,</hi> chaunged their Religion? I am ſure they neuer changed, but kept ſtill the ſame, which was deliuered to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their firſt Apoſtles. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Proteſtantes beginning but ſome fiftie or threeſcore yeares agoe, haue in this ſmall time ſo chopped &amp; chaunged, ſo altered, and transformed theyr Religion, as you may well ſaye Proteus, in regard of them to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in ſhape: wherin they ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues like theyr Fathers the old He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes,<note place="margin">Greg. lib. 3 mor. expo ſit. in Iob. cap. 19.</note> who alſo in inconſtancy of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine were very notable: and no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, for when they be once foorth of the right waie, they take euerie pathe which offereth it ſelfe vnto them, but neuer can happen vpon the right way againe, except they goe backe from whence they came, but runne ſtil fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">2. tim. 3.</note> and further out of the vvay, <hi>euer learning, but neuer comming to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Trueth.</hi> This inconſtancy &amp; chaunge in Doctrine was ſo great in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13600:52"/>
               <hi>Luther</hi> his followers,<note place="margin">Riuander in lupo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coriato fol 73.</note> as that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues complained therof. And heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is that the <hi>Lutheranes</hi> are ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie chaunged into <hi>Zwinglians,</hi> or <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſtes, Caluiniſtes</hi> into <hi>Anabaptiſtes,</hi> or <hi>Arrians, Anabaptiſts</hi> into <hi>Libertines, Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſtes,</hi> or into the <hi>Family of Loue.</hi> And this lenity they haue (as they haue all their other <hi>Capricches</hi>) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <hi>Luther,</hi> whoſe inconſtancy in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is moſt notable. For at his firſt beginning, hee proteſted that he only miſliked the abuſe of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> and in no wiſe the <hi>Indulgences</hi> themſelues. A litle after he plainly deſpiſed the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences</hi> themſelues.<note place="margin">Vlemberg. cauſa 12. pag. 391.</note> Then he began to call in queſtion the authoritye of the <hi>Pope,</hi> afterwardes <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little going forwarde, at the length, he denied <hi>Free-will,</hi> &amp; rowling vp and downe as it were a ſnowe-ball of hereſie, made the ſame bigger and bigger, in ſuch ſorte as he came to that audacitye, that he burned openly at <hi>Wittenberge,</hi> the bookes of the Canon Lawe, affirming the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> &amp; the catholike church to be the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13600:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Synagogue, and ſtewes of Sathan: yet ſtayed he himſelfe not ſo, but ſtil plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Proteus euen vnto his end: for at <hi>Wormes</hi> before the Emperour, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he profeſſed himſelf an enimy to the Church, yet he maintained the ſacrifice of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> &amp; ſaid it ſtil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as alſo prayer to Saintes for the dead, Purgatory, Communion vnder one kind, &amp; many ſuch like Catholike points, all which 9. yeares after, before the ſame Emperour he vtterly denied. The ſame inconſtancy was in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <hi>Melanchton, Caluin, Bucer,</hi> and in them of <hi>Wittenberge,</hi> in the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes, and in ſuch like, as alſo in your Proteſtantes there in England. And I pray you vvhat a chaunging, and turning in and out was there of your COMMVNION Booke? For firſt the deuiſers thereof highly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, and affirmed it to be agreeable to Chriſts inſtitution, &amp; to the ſeruice of the Primitiue Church; and a while after they vtterly miſliked it, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>authoriſing it, they ſet foorth another in principall pointes quite contrary to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13600:53"/>
the former, &amp; yet they affirmed that alſo to be according to Chriſts inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; iump as the vſe was in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church. And yet how this is approued, &amp; liked of your Preachers, &amp; miniſters, you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but know, who ſee &amp; behold ſuch carping, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fault thereat, and ſuch contempt therof, as that the Miniſter who doth obſerue duely the order thereof, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a temporizer, or a cold Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant (I might ſay an Atheiſt) for his labour. And he who can moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it, and can wed, burie, baptize, miniſter the Communion, and doe ſuch like, after ſome other new faſhion of his owne inuenting, is accounted a iollie fellow, &amp; a man of zeale. What ſtirre is there (I pray you) in euerie ſheire, yea almoſt in euerie pariſh, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Miniſters obſeruing the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this theyr booke of COMMON PRAYER? What holde and tye is there betweene the Pariſhioners and theyr Curate? What a doe is there, and hath beene from the beginning about the Communion? One vvhile
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13600:54"/>
it muſt be done in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, &amp; leauened Bread: by and by not ſo, but in vnlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uened Bread, after in loafe Bread, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thogh your cup euer had wine in it, till now of late that ſom do begin to take inſteed therof good nappy ale: the like inconſtancie you might ſee in placing the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion table: for firſt it muſt be placed in the middle of the quire, then in the bodie of the church, after in the <hi>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel</hi> again as the altar was: one while the miniſter muſt turne his face tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards the ſouth, another while towards the north, and another while towards the eaſt: wherby al wiſe men may ſee, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your religion firſt began, and neuer was in the vvorld before: for if euer it had bin before, you might ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly haue had ſome preſident, by which you might haue ordered theſe things. And to ſpeake plainelie what I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, I finde a great cauſe of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie in Doctrine to be aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and diſaduantage: for your reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is framed only to ſerue turnes, &amp; times: for when they were but few in number, by wreſting the Scriptures,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13600:54"/>
they taught that Chriſtes flocke vvas but little,<note place="margin">Iewell in Apol.</note> and therefore they gloried much in theyr ſmall number: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that their opinions were ſpreade through <hi>Germanie, Fraunce, Englande, Scotland,</hi> and in other Countries they vaunted much, and argued that theyr Doctrine muſt needs be true, becauſe it was ſpread ſo largely. When it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their turne they ſtoutly defended with tooth and nayle,<note place="margin">Goodman Knoxe.</note> that a woman might not lawfully gouerne a realme, no not in ciuill, or temporall matters: but within a while after, when it fitted their purpoſe, they taught as they yet doe, that a woman may rule a realme, not only in temporall thinges, but the Church alſo in ſpiritual cauſes. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſerued their turne,<note place="margin">Luth. tom. 3. Ger. Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. fol. 115.</note> they taught that it was a horible thing to put me to death for Religion, and expreſly againſt the word of god: but when they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſword, they cried out in ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s on the contrary ſide, &amp; neuer left off, vntil it was decred by publike authori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, that thoſe who wer not of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhuld ſuffer death therfore. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:13600:55"/>
it fitted their purpoſe,<note place="margin">Tom. 5. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ger. f. 157. a &amp; f. 444. &amp; 159. &amp; 491. Tom. 1. Germ. fol. 537. Colloq. Menſ. f 4. in fine lib. ſeſ. 3. b</note> they taught that none ought to preach, but he who was allowed, and licenſed by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, afterwarde vpon other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; they wrote that a Chriſtian man may without leaue of any perſon take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him that function. One while they taught that the BIBLE was the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and the moſt eaſieſt booke in the worlde to bee vnderſtoode, another<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while they wrote vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduantage, that it was vnpoſſible for any man to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande throughly any one worde in the Bible, for that it was ſo obſcure &amp; profound. One while they taught that no Commentaries of SCRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVRES written by men,<note place="margin">Melancth. in Loc. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ann. 1524.</note> muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, yea that they muſt be ſhunned as a plague or peſtilence, anotherwhile they themſelues ſet forth Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Poſtilles, and obtruded them to the people.<note place="margin">To. 2. Ger. fol. 255. a &amp; f. 404. a</note> One while they teache that all men ought to be iudges of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine &amp; religion, another-while they teache that no man, no not an Angel, muſt iudge thereof. And a thowſand ſuch like contradictions &amp; proofes of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13600:55"/>
vnconſtancy, and chaunge maye you find in their doctrine, which here fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to account would be ouer tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. I vvill therefore end with the ſaying of <hi>Gregorie</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxonie: We doe know what theſe fellowes doe teach this yeare, but what they will teach the next yeare we cannot geſſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="reason">
            <head>THE XVIII. REASON. Falſe Prophets and Teachers.</head>
            <p>THe Prophets, Apoſtles, &amp; Chriſt himſelfe fore-tolde that in the latter dayes there ſhould come falſe Prophets, and to the end wee ſhould take heed of them, they painted them foorth in their colours, whereby they might eaſilie be knowne. Now it can not be denyed, but that wee be in the latter dayes, and therefore we muſt be verie vigilant, and watchfull to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, &amp; to know theſe ſeducers when they come. And conferring the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers afore-ſaide with the manners of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13600:56"/>
theſe Proteſtants, we doe plainly ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they be the verie ſame vvhich were foretold, and as it were, pointed at by the finger of God: for firſt they come vnſent,<note place="margin">Ierm. 13.</note> as <hi>Ieremie</hi> fore-tolde in theſe wordes. <hi>I did not ſende them, and they did runne:</hi> for certaine it is, that they neyther haue orders, as they ought to haue, nor any Conſecration, or right calling: for they were not ſent by the Catholike Church as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, but vtterly condemned for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, and when any of them is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the Romane Religion, they plainely ſee that they haue no more to doe with any ſpirituall function the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laymen haue. But on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide, if any Prieſt of the Catholike Church become an Apoſtata by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking his religion, if he profeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Proteſtant they account and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme ſuch a one, very fitt for theyr Miniſtry, yea and more worthie then one of theyr owne making: for that they aſſure themſelues, &amp; ſo confeſſe, that the Catholiks haue ordinary cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling moſt lawfull: but they neyther
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13600:56"/>
haue ordinary calling as is moſt plain: nor extraordinarie, for that they can worke no miracle to proue the ſame: <hi>Ergo</hi> no calling at all, but they come of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnſent for. Then are they, as it was Prophicied of them like their Fathers, ſmooth tongued fellowes,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> which with ſweet ſpeeches, &amp; pleaſant clawings deceiue the harts of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and haue a ſhow of godlines,<note place="margin">2. Tim.</note> but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the vertue thereof: for they crie out. <hi>The word of the Lord, the light of the Gospel, the only Paſsion of our Sauiour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Reg. 22.</note> 
               <hi>no ſin to the Elect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.14.23. &amp; 27. Iſay. cap. 3</note> 
               <hi>al are cleane which beleeue their Doctrine:</hi> vvith a thouſand ſuch like plauſible ſpeeches, as the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did in times paſt. But conſider them well, &amp; you ſhall finde them to be lying maiſters, and deceauers,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. &amp; 3.</note> who doe not only them-ſelues walke after the fleſh in concupiſcence of vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but doe alſo draw others in the deſire of luſt, and leacherie, promiſing libertie, whereas they themſelues are ſlaues of corruption,<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> and in few words they lead the people the broad vvaie to perdition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:13600:57"/>This you may plainelie ſee by that which hath beene ſaid before, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would haue you to iudge whea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be like that the Proteſtants be thoſe falſe teachers which were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde, or no. Surely in mine opinion, there are al things in them which were fore ſhewed to be in the falſe prophets, and ſeducers of the latter dayes.<note place="margin">Ier. 29.23.</note> They come vnſent, they teache plauſible thinges to fleſh and blood, they teach theyr own fanſies, and ſay they be the words of the Lord,<note place="margin">Ezech. 13.</note> wreſting &amp; wrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the Scriptures as they liſt, they colour and ſet out theyr cauſe in ſuch braue tearmes, and with ſuch fraunde and deceit, as if it were poſsible the verie Elect might be drawne into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> they make a ſhow as they vvere the Apoſtles of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> and thereby they ſeduce the innocent, they know not that God vſeth them as a ſcourge,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> and that hee tempteth his people by them,<note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> they make an outward ſhow of humanitie, of peace and concord, and of ſuch like, putting vpon them the cloathing of ſheepe,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> but they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:13600:57"/>
according to the Flemmiſh Proteſtants prouerbe Bares in wolues places.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="reason">
            <head>THE XIX. REASON. Lyars, ſlaunderers, &amp; reuylers.</head>
            <p>IT ſeemeth that the Proteſtantes haue eyther no conſcience at all, or els that it is ſeared with an hoate iron, for that they make no boanes to beare ſo manifeſtlie falſe witnes againſt their neighbours, in charging the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, &amp; all theyr Elders with ſo plaine vntruthes, and in ſlaundering and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiling they care not whome in a moſt iniurious, and opprobrious manner. And a moſt pittifull thing it is, to ſee the ſimple people drawne away from the true Religion of theyr Elders by ſuch ſhamefull meanes: for euery man of vnderſtanding may eaſily ſee howe they make lying <hi>theyr helpe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 28.</note> 
               <hi>and defende themſelues thereby.</hi> And yet doe theyr miſerable adhaerentes beleeue euerie
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:13600:58"/>
thing to be goſpel which they ſay, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer going about to trie out the trueth therof. To this ſhameful ſhift are they driuen (as they be to many others) for that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not otherwiſe excuſe their departure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ancient Church: for if they had litle or nothing to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, euery ſimple ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile why they left it. They faine ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; make vpon their owne fingers many horrible things concerning the doctrine, ceremonies, &amp; condition of the ſaid Church. And this they doe in places where they dominier &amp; raigne, where they know no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dare ſhew his face to defend the cauſe of the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> world. And no meruaile though they deale thus with the Catholik Church, when as they ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der &amp; tel lyes of ech other, as the <hi>Luherans</hi> beare witnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Sacramentaries,</hi> the <hi>Maioriſts,</hi> againſt the <hi>Flacians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vlenber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius cauſa. 10.</note> and both theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> &amp; other Sectaries one againſt another. And to giue you a litle taſte of their dealings I wil put down a few of their ſayings, but brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for that I doubt I be ouer tedious.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:13600:58"/>
1 They ſay that Chriſt was vnknown before their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming,<note place="margin">In poſtilla Germ. An. 1537. part. 2. fol. 141.</note> &amp; that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel lay in the duſt, &amp; was hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, &amp; <hi>Luther</hi> doubteth whether <hi>Germany</hi> euer heard the word of God before he preached it. Which thing if it were true, then vndoubtedlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite people, yea al Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome was deceiued vnder the name of Chriſt, for 1500. yeres togeather, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlie were all damned. And how impudent a lie is it, that Chriſt vvas not knowne before their comming? wheras al churches throughout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e did by pictures, and externall ceremonies ſet before the eies of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Death, blood, Croſſe &amp; Paſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Sauiour? was there not in euery rode loft the picture of Chriſt crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? And did not the very ſtones, wals, &amp; ſumptuous buildings declare, that the erectors therof were me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only beleeuing in Chriſt, but alſo moſt ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, &amp; forward to ſet forth his honor, by furthering his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; 10000 ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt proofes might here be brought forth againſt this ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cles lie of theyrs.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:13600:59"/>
2. They inculcate, and euen dull the eares of the people, with often telling them of the Idolatry of their elders, &amp; affirme it to be more abominable tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Idolatry of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> or <hi>Heathens:</hi> And although they be ſo deuided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, as that they accuſe one another of that crime, yet in this they all agree, as Pilate &amp; Herod did in putting Chriſt to death, but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe being mortall enimies, the one to the other. But vntill they proue this Idolatry, which they neuer could, nor neuer wil be able to doe, I cannot but deeme it an intolerable lye and cauill, the which is more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by almoſt innumerable argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which are to be ſeene in many learned writers.<note place="margin">Aug. conf in artic. de Miſſa.</note> 3. They ſay that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes holde, that Chriſt ſatisfied onely for Originall ſinne, and that he ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Maſſe for other ſinnes; which to be a moſt manifeſt lie, all the bokes written of this matter by Catholike Diuines doe plainely teſtifie.<note place="margin">Aug. conf. tit de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectu ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum.</note> 4 They affirme that the Catholikes doe teach, that by choice of meates, and by other
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:13600:59"/>
humane conſtitutions, remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins, &amp; ſaluation is obtained, &amp; that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the doers are iuſtified. Which is a lye ſo manifeſt as it needeth no confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. 5. They ſay howe the Papiſtes holde that if a man be Contrite, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and haue done Satisfaction for his ſinnes,<note place="margin">In artic. Smalcal. dic. in artic 3. fal pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. papiſt.</note> that he is therby iuſt before God without Chriſt, or faith, which is a lye no leſſe ſhamefull than the other. For the Catholikes teache, that no Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is had, no ſinne forgiuen, no good thing obtained, but by the Paſſion of our Sauiour Chriſt. 6. They affirme, that the Papiſts doe worſhip Saints in ſteed of Chriſt, &amp; doe honour them as Gods, which is a groſe impudent lye as euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth.<note place="margin">Hadd cont Oſorium.</note> 7. They are not aſhamed to write, that Religion was not changed in <hi>England</hi> but by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Biſhops, &amp; that the landes, &amp; goods of Abbies &amp; Religious hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, were diſtributed to Godly vſes, as to Schooles, Vniuerſities &amp; Hoſpitals. And that the <hi>Pope</hi> for an ordinary tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to him yeerely paide, giueth free leaue vnder his great ſeale to Prieſtes,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13600:60"/>
to keepe concubines openly without controlement. And the like lies they lay vpon the auncient Fathers, as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> ſaid of <hi>S. Auſten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Apol. tit. de pec. orig.</note> that he taught Originall ſinne to be taken awaye in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> not that it was not any more, but that it was not imputed. Whereas <hi>S. Austen</hi> ſpoke not there of Originall ſin, but of concpiſcence. So they ſay <hi>S. Bernard</hi> reca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted monachiſme at his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ende,<note place="margin">Luth. tom. 5. Ien. ger. fol. 457. Teleman. Heſhuſ. l. 1. de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ec. p. 60.</note> &amp; that moſt of auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; Fathers retracted, &amp; reuoked before they died the Doctrine which they had written; or elſe, that they thought otherwiſe than they wrote, &amp; ſpoke. By this meanes to defend their newe doctrine, &amp; to ſhift off the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, which are altogether plainly againſt it, they are conſtrained to lay two notable lies vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the one that they recalled their doctrine before their death, the other that they wrote, &amp; ſpoke one thing, but thought another. And no maruell though they ſlaunder, &amp; wrong in this Atheiſtical manner the Holy Fathers, when as ſome of them ſpare not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:13600:60"/>
themſelues. If the three Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 3. Ien. Ger. fol. 261.</note> (ſaith <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>) had not held their tackle, about Faith without works, al the multitude had failed therin, &amp; <hi>Iames</hi> ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled in it. But of this kind of ſtuffe I wil not here alleadge any more; he who deſireth to hear moe of their lies, &amp; ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, may find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboundantly ſet down by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe &amp; ſundry authors at this day, but yet take with you this ſaying of your <hi>M. Luther, He who once lieth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 1. Germ. fol. 423.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>certainly is not of God, &amp; is worthily ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in all things.</hi> And as for reuiling, &amp; railing, I thinke that Lucifer himſelfe coulde little haue exceeded the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants therein, &amp; eſpecially their firſt Apoſtle, the ſaide <hi>Martine Luther,</hi> who with filthy, beaſtly, ſcuruy, &amp; oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious ſpeeches, ſo be daubeth the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church, &amp; the magiſtrats ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as euery one may ſee what ſpirite poſſeſſed his heart, the ſame out of all doubt which delighteth in filthineſſe &amp; ſcurrility. And to the end you may haue ſome aime what kinde of fellowe this Arche-apoſtle of your proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13600:61"/>
was, I wil here brieflie ſet downe a few words of his filthie mouth. Hee calleth the Archbiſhip of <hi>Ments,</hi> being a Prince Elector, &amp; deſcended of the Princely Electorall familie of <hi>Brande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom 3. Germ. fol. 533. a. b. &amp; f. 326. 360. col. menſ. f. 342. 343.</note> 
               <hi>a fraudulent, a moſt ſhamefull lyar, a ſhifting Biſhop, a filthie ſhitten Prieſt, an hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Cardinall, a great, &amp; a notable Epicure, an impudent and euill worme, a damned and loſt man, a craftie ſcoffer, the greateſt knaue that euer was except Nero, &amp; Caligula, &amp;c.</hi> Hee reuileth the Princes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,<note place="margin">Tom. 5. Germ. in gloſſa. ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per edictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperat.</note> which did meete at the Diet at <hi>Angusta,</hi> Anno. 1530. calling them, <hi>traitours, wicked men, the diuels ſeruantes, knaues, madde hogges, great and groſſe aſſes.</hi> Hee calleth the Princes of <hi>Germanie, fooles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 3. fol. 195. b. &amp; fol. 200 &amp; 190. Tom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſcales, and bubles of the Pope, Gods Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beers, and hangemen, Germane beasts, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels puppies, &amp;c.</hi> Hee braggeth that he eſteemed the King of <hi>England,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Catholike Princes as miſerable beggers, dizzards and fooles, vvhich make him paſtime, and as new n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttes, which he would haue to glorie and to ſing in this manner. <hi>Here wee nits doe ſit vpon the head of the nobleſt beaſt in the earth
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:13600:61"/>
in his haire, wee are of a baſe lynage, lice are our Parents, thoſe great Giants, which killed euen Scilla the Romane Emperour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 3. Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ger. f. 331. &amp; f. 334.a.</note> 
               <hi>and many others. What haue wee to doe with</hi> Luther <hi>a begger, it is true you are nits, but yet you are not lice.</hi> And in his infamous libell againſt the ſaid King of England, hee hath great ſtore of oprobrious titles and names, as: <hi>Henrie by the inclemencie of God, King of England, King of lyes. &amp;c.</hi> So dealt hee vvith that moſte famous Prince, <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 2. Ger. fol. 206. a. &amp; Tom. 6. f. 6.</note> calling him a Tyrant, freneticall, mad, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed corporally of the diuell, the diuels Apoſtle, &amp;c. And in his infamous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell entituled: <hi>Wider hans, worſt,</hi> hee calleth <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke, a groſſe aſſe, a ſtocke, a tronke, an impudent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar, a mad man, lunatike, damned, the theefe on the left hand, aſſe of all aſſes in Wolfen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butell, a pudding, a ſauſage, an houſe-firer, who ſtuffeth him-ſelfe not by drinking wine, but by deuouring and drinking Diuelles, a fearefull &amp; fugitiue knaue, a doting eunuch, Prince of cut throats, a broudy dogge,</hi> &amp; by a thouſand ſuch like names. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholike diuines, yea, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13600:62"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:13600:62"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:13600:63"/>
againſt his own of-ſpring the <hi>Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries.</hi> Ieſu, what terms vſeth he, where he hath ſo often that malepert interie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Trotz, Swinglius</hi> ſetting forth the ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> in his colours, bringeth him in this maner reuiling:<note place="margin">In reſp. a. v. a.</note> 
               <hi>Swe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mer, a knaue, a diuell, a theefe, an hypocrite, Trotz, Botz, Plotz, Plitz, tonitru, po, pu, pa, plump, &amp;c.</hi> And when he had put the word <hi>(Sola)</hi> of his own braine into the text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. beeing admoniſhed by ſome of it, he braied out &amp; ſaid,<note place="margin">Tom. 5. Germ. fol. 141. &amp; fol. 144.</note> 
               <hi>Doctor Martine Luther will ſo,</hi> &amp; affirmeth, <hi>that a Papiſt, and an aſſe are all one, I wil haue it ſo, I commaund it ſo,</hi> &amp; againe, <hi>Luther will ſo, &amp; ſaith, that he is a doctor, aboue all the doctors in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy.</hi> Yea afterward it repented him, that he had not corrupted the text of the Apoſtle worſe in putting in more of his owne head, and that he had not made the Apoſtle to ſay: <hi>We ſuppoſe a man to be iuſtified by faith only, without all works of al Lawes.</hi> And many moe ſuch like outrages I could here ſet down of his, but I hope theſe maye ſuffice to make you to knowe what a milde and modeſt man this reformer of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:13600:63"/>
worlde was, and what a notable ring leader you haue in your Religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="reason">
            <head>THE XX. REASON. Keeping in memory Gods benefits.</head>
            <p>GOd almighty hauing beſtowed infinite benefits vpon man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning euen at his creation, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded chiefely at his hands, as a ſigne &amp; token of gratitude and thankefulneſſe that he woulde be mindefull of them, and neuer by any meanes ſuffer them to depart out of his memory. And this was the cauſe of ſo many Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies &amp; of the Celebration of ſo manie Feates amongeſt the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> The like hath the Catholike ROMANE Church done, by ordaining diuers &amp; ſundry feaſts for the due worſhiping of God, in yelding thankful, &amp; liuely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebrance of ſpecial benefits receiued at his hands, &amp; namely of the benefite of Redemption, (which without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon ſurpaſſeth all the reſt) by call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yeerly to minde, &amp; by ſetting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eies of hir children in a moſt vniforme maner al that our Sauior did &amp; ſuffered for vs, as his Conception,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13600:64"/>
his Aduent, his Natiuity, his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, his Manifeſtation, his Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, his Baptiſme, his Faſting, his Preaching, his Miracles, his Paſſion, his Death, his Burial, his Reſurrection, his Aſcention, his ſending down of the Holy Ghoſt, his ſecond Aduent, &amp;c. The which are Celebrated, Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and recalled to memory in a moſt ſolmne, and decent manner, with ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories moſt apte &amp; fitte for euery ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and with exacte application of all Shadowes, Figures, Promiſes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, and with ſuch like out of the olde Teſtament, as maye teſtifie and confirme the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith, at Chrſt-Maſſe, at Candle-Maſſe, at Shro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide, at Lent, at Eaſter, at Whitſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide, and at other ſeaſons of the yeere. And I woulde to God that you were but once preſent here vpon Chriſt-Maſſe Eue at night, and vpon Chriſt-Maſſe Day, to beholde the liuelye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of our Lords Birthe. Oh what Torches, what Tapers, what Lights, what Singing, what Senſing, what Mirth, what Melody, what play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:13600:64"/>
vpon Organes, and other Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, what praying vpon Bookes &amp; Beades, what weeping for ioy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, and what a number of goodlie Ceremonies ſhould you ſee? And as great ſolemnitie is at other times of the yeare befitting the ſeaſon. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all that our Redeemer did for vs is moſt liuelie, and moſt freſhly renewed in the memorie of mankinde. Beſides all this, there are alſo celebrated, and that verie ſolemnely the birth dayes, (not into this world, but into heauen) of his Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſours, Virgins, and the feaſtes of his bleſſed Mother. By all which there is a kind of heauen vpon earth, Chriſt with his Saints and Angels being continuallie ſeene here after a ſort as he is there, in face and fruition. Thus is he honoured in himſelfe, thus is he worſhiped in his Angels, thus is he praiſed in his Saints, And to al this may be added the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of euery particular materiall Church, which Feaſt in England you vſually call the Wakes, being a moſte ſolemne Feaſt, to put the Pariſhioners
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:13600:65"/>
in minde of that triumphant Church in heauen, vvhich they daylie trauaile towardes, &amp; to recal, &amp; refreſh in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory the day that their pariſh church was firſt dedicated to God, or to ſome one of his Saintes, vvho in particular ſort hath the protection thereof, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring thereby their gratitude, and thankefulnes to God for his benefitts of Redemption, and calling. All theſe Feaſtes, and ſolemnities (I ſay) doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new and retaine in the memorie of man the actes and benefittes of his Redeemer, and doe mooue and ſtirre vppe his ſtonie heart to loue him, prayſe him, and to ſerue him; they doe ſette before his eyes, the holie liues, and happie deaths of his bleſſed Saintes, thereby to make vs to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them, to honour GOD by them, and to praie to them to be a meanes to him for vs, that we maie hereafter enioy their bleſſed company for euer. Manie other thinges hath the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church ordayned, thereby to keepe continuallie in the minde of man the matters afore-ſaide, as Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13600:65"/>
Pictures, Images, and Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in euerie common place, &amp; high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, vvhich people beholding, may preſentlie conuerte theyr minde to ſome heauenlie miſterie repreſented thereby. And by theſe meanes the moſte vnlearned amongeſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vvere they young Maidens, or olde Wiues, knew more of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtian religion, then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of your Miniſters daughters, or their wiues, yea or ſome of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters them-ſelues doe knowe. And no marueile, when as they haue abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and abrogated in a manner all Ceremonies, and after a ſorte, all feaſts, and thoſe who hold themſelues the pureſt, doe altogether lay away all Ceremonies, &amp; Feaſtes, in ſuch ſort as you may ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe all kind of work, yea vpon Chriſtmaſſe day it ſelf, &amp; to make no more account thereof, then of anie worke day in the whole yeare. And they all haue aboliſhed gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie all Shrines, Pictures, Images, Crucifixes, Monumentes, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thinge vvhich might preſent to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:13600:66"/>
the minde of the beholder any Miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or Document of Chriſtian Faith, or any good example to be followed, &amp; they haue leaft their churches as fit to mooue people to pietie and deuotion, as theyr barnes are, when all the corne and hay is out of them, and nothing left to be ſeene beſides the roofes, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and ſilles. Conſider here with your ſelues, whether Iewes, Turks, or Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, if they had gotten any Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like countries, could haue made grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpoile in the churches, or haue left them more bare, then the Proteſtants haue done? Or wheather Chriſtians, if they had vanquiſhed Heathen coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, could haue dealt otherwiſe with the churches of theyr Idols, then the Proteſtantes haue done with Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Churches? And beſides this, they haue defaced &amp; throwne down Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Market places, &amp; in high waies, as though they would not ſuffer, nor endure, that people by beholding any ſuch thing ſhould remember and call to minde the Paſsion of their Sauiour. This out of all doubt, was no ſmal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13600:66"/>
of the Diuel to mooue them, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome other pretence, to make &amp; rid all away, that ſhould retaine and keepe in peoples mindes that, which chieflie they ought euer to haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of their minde. And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie rediculous it is to ſee them keepe ſuch a ſtirre about keeping Holie the Sabboth, reiecting al other holy daies: whereas they haue no more vvarrant for the ſolemnizing of the Sondaie, then they haue for S. <hi>Laurence</hi> his day, or for any other holy, or feſtiuall daie in all the yeare: for other reaſon or warrant they haue not, but the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Catholike Roman Church, which inſtituted, and ordained all Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiual dayes by the ſame Commiſsion, that it chaunged the Sabboth of the Iewes, which was vpon Saturday, into the Sabboth of the Chriſtians, vvhich it ordained to be vppon Sunday. And in time, I aſſure my ſelf, if they ſhould proceede on, the Diuell would bring them to lay away Sunday alſo (as hee hath cauſed ſome to doe alreadie) and conſequently the Word and all: and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13600:67"/>
ſo driue them to plaine Atheiſme, to which many of their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to alreadie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="reason">
            <head>THE XXI. REASON. The Proteſtantes beginning, and proceeding againſt then conſciences.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In colloq. menſ. Ger. fol. 458. b. &amp; 369. b.</note>I Know that no man can ſee into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans hart or conſcience, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Luther,</hi> and his followers brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that they could ſo doe) and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we cannot iudge thereof by ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition only; but yet wee may be bold to giue our cenſure of them, by the plaine wordes, and manifeſt deedes of the parties. Wee dare not be ſo raſh in this matter as the Proteſtantes are, who by onely coniectures iudge the harts of one another, and ſticke not to write,<note place="margin">Tom. 1. Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ger. fol. 4. coll. menſ. fol. 244. a. Tom. 2. Ger. Ien. fol. 9. b.</note> that they ſpeake and write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences &amp; knowledge: whereby we may gather that they vſe ſo to do: for otherwiſe how could they ſuſpect ſuch a deteſtable fault in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for commonlie a man <hi>thinketh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:13600:67"/>
to be as himſelfe is.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. menſ. fol. 10. b.</note> 
               <hi>Luther</hi> confeſſeth that hee began this Tragedie againſt his conſcience, &amp; therfore he thought others to doe the like. <hi>Zwinglius</hi> ſaith, that he beleeued not the <hi>Reall Preſence</hi> for manie yeares together before hee brake off from the Catholike Church, but yet hee vvarilie diſſembled his mind, &amp; outwardly ſhewing himſelfe a Papiſt,<note place="margin">Collo menſ. fol. 53.</note> and in his opinion others doe the like. <hi>Nenno</hi> openly telleth that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was an <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> hee ſought after nothing, but his bellie,<note place="margin">In adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nition ad do</note> &amp; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the fleſh, and therefore hee thought that all Catholicke Prieſtes did the like: but you may aske me, if <hi>Luther,</hi> who firſt began the proteſtants Religion, had at his entry ſuch repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of conſcience, why did hee not leaue off that courſe, &amp; returne to his Cloyſter againe. I anſwere; for that he had proceeded ſo farre, as he himſelfe thought, that by deſperate neceſſitie hee muſt goe on, howſoeuer the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter would fal out. Euen as <hi>Iu. Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suetonius in vita Cae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaris.</note> who doubted much, and had diuers Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bats with himſelf, whether he ſhuld march
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:13600:68"/>
forward with his army againſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes or no: but at the length when he had proceeded ſo farre, as that hee had paſſed ouer the riuer <hi>Rubicon,</hi> hee burſt out into theſe words: <hi>Now is the chaunce throwne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. menſ. fol. 241.</note> 
               <hi>now muſt we needs proceed wheather we will or no.</hi> In like manner <hi>Luther,</hi> after he had gone further then his conſcience woulde haue ſuffered him to haue done, hee vtterly diſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the recouery of his credit (much like as one <hi>Thomas Bell</hi> who yet liueth, in England, hath done) iuſtified his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,<note place="margin">Col. menſ. fol. 158. b. 273. b.</note> and ſo began his hell in this life, hauing his conſcience euer after vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, and ſtill reproouing him, &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to repent, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did, for that he had proceeded ſo farre, and to wiſh all his Bookes buried in the earth,<note place="margin">In praefat. in tom. 1. Germ. Ien.</note> and was ſo troubled in diſputations that as one ready to die, he would goe out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the next chamber, and there throw himſelfe vpon a bed. And yet for all this,<note place="margin">Melanct. in vita Luth. pag. 13.</note> the Diuell at the laſt grew ſo big with him, as that hee made him in all deſperation to breake out into all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt the Catholicke Church
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:13600:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
without any regarde of conſcience,<note place="margin">Tom. 3. Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ger. f. 274</note> or honeſtie; as you may ſee by that hee flatlie ſayeth, that if the Councell of Trent would allow Communion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both kindes (which he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taught to be inſtituted by Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of neceſsitie muſt ſo be done) yet he and his followers, would in deſpite of the Councel, either vſe but one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or none at all, and would plainelie account them accurſed, which ſhould vſe both kinds by the authority of the Councell. And in like maner he ſaith, that if the Catholicke Church, ſhould by any Councell decree that Prieſtes, and Eccleſiaſticall perſons might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie marrie, (which Doctrine he him ſelfe not only taught,<note place="margin">Tom. 2. Ger. f. 214.</note> but euen practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame by marrying a Nunne) he would rather diſſemble &amp; beleeue, that that man was more in Gods fauor who all his life long, ſhould keepe one or two, yea or three whoores, then he who after the decree of the Councell ſhould marrie, yea he would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund vnder paine of damnation, that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by permition of the Councell ſhould
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:13600:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
marry, but either liue chaſte, or if he cannot ſo doe, by keeping a who are he ſhould not deſpaire. So plaied he about the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> for although he taught that the Eleuation of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament was wicked and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Idolatry, and therfore would haue it abrogated,<note place="margin">Tom. 3. Ien. Germ</note> yet after that he had vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode that his aduerſary <hi>Carolaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> did teach the ſame, he to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict &amp; to oppoſe himſelfe againſt him, retained &amp; kept the Eleuation in <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberge,</hi> whole twenty yeeres togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, mauger the head of his ſaid emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator <hi>Carolaſtadius.</hi> Yea he openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, that rather than hee woulde yeelde an haires breadth to him, he would goe and be a Friar againe, and obſerue all orders in his Monaſtery, as duely as euer he had done before. The like courſe he toke about other things, and namely, about Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Becauſe the Papiſts</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doe vrge Tranſubſtantiation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. 2. Germ. fol. 225.</note> 
               <hi>we onely that we may be contrary to them, &amp; inſulte againſt them, will beleeue that true Breade, &amp; true Wine doe there remaine together with the Body &amp;
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:13600:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Bloode of Chriſt.</hi> Yet ſaide he of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation againſt the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, that he woulde rather beleeue it with the Papiſtes, than he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the Reall Preſence with them. This maye you plainly ſee, that this your firſt Apoſtle and generall Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all you Proteſtantes, had no conſcience, nor Religion at all, but ledde by a ſpirite of contradiction, he ſought to be ſingular in himſelfe, and contrary to all others. Neither did hee onely in this manner againſt his conſcience, but his companions and Schollers were alſo in the ſame predicament, and had the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance in themſelues.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Melancthon</hi> in the diet at <hi>Aspurge</hi> was ſo troubled in conſcience,<note place="margin">Chytraeus in hiſt. Aug. conf.</note> that he was altogeather ſadde, puſillanimous, and doubtfull in minde, and gaue him ſelfe ſo to weeping, as that no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes, nor encouragementes coulde preuaile, or doe him any good.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Carolaſtadius</hi> openly confeſſed that what hee did was cleane againſt his conſcience.<note place="margin">Col. m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger. f. 1 &amp; 517.</note> The like repugning
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:13600:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
conſcience had <hi>Zwinglius</hi> in expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the words of our Sauiour of the B. Sacrament,<note place="margin">Lib. de cae na. page. 216. a.</note> as witneſſeth <hi>Kemnitius,</hi> and the <hi>Lutherans</hi> write, that hee openlie ſhewed, and declared in his manners, geſts, and in all things that his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence accuſed him of errours:<note place="margin">Ioannes Shutz in ſerp. antiq. fol. 19.</note> but yet he had leifer forſake the truth, then to looſe his honour in yeelding to <hi>Luther.</hi> The like write the ſame <hi>Lutherans</hi> of <hi>Oecolampadius.</hi> And as for <hi>Bucer</hi> it is wel knowne, that hee had no conſcience, nor religion at all: for at <hi>Wittenberge</hi> he was a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> at <hi>Colone</hi> halfe a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, in <hi>England</hi> a <hi>Zwinglian,</hi> &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where of euerie Sect. I could eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew the like dealing againſt theyr conſciences, and knowledge in diuers other principall Proteſtants, &amp; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in your countriman <hi>I well,</hi> who in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and coating Scriptures, Doctors, Councels, and other Authors, doth ſo rent and teare in peeces the text, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the ſenſe, chaunge and alter the words, and pull out of the ſentence by peece meale ſome little parcell, which is forced to ſound for his purpoſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:13600:70"/>
as he cannot but ſee plainelie, that the Author ſpeaketh cleane contrarie, as any man may wonder to ſee a man ſo deſperatly and damnably ſhameleſſe, as openly, &amp; in the view of the whole world to ſhew himſelfe without God, or conſcience: but mine intended bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie will not admit any moe allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this place. When I had found out the Premiſſes to bee moſte true, and had duelie weighed with my ſelfe the dealinges of theſe new Goſpellers, I thought it better to aduenture my ſoule vvith all the vvhole Chriſtian world of all ages who had their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences moſt quiet, caulme, and ioyfull, then with a few deſperate fellows, who thus deale againſt their owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and conſciences, and ſo ſhewe themſelues moſt impudent, &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to the whole world.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="reason">
            <head>THE XXII. REASON. Vnreuerent dealing.</head>
            <p>THE Catholike Romane Church hath euer both in doing, &amp; ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and euery manner of way borne
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13600:71"/>
great repect, and reuerence towardes Gods holy Saints, and towards all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things in regard of him, from whom proceedeth all holines, as in reuerent entring into the Church, in reuerent taking of holie-water, in reuerent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour towards the holy Aultars, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards pictures, &amp; images of the ſaints of God, in reuerent and meeke knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in reuerent &amp; deuout praying, in all reuerence and attention at the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Maſſe, and in euery action, and ieſt which Catholikes vſe in the Church, you may ſee great reuerence, &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble veneration: But contrariwiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Proteſtants as all thinges are prophane, ſo are they moſte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely vſed. They enter into theyr Churches with no greater reuerence the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they enter into tauerns, they bow or make reuerence to nothing therin, for that they haue made all Sacred things away, if any of them kneele, it is but vpon thornes, for full ſoone are they vp againe, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with their hats vpon their heads they eyther iangle, or talke, or walke, or ſitte ſtaring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:13600:71"/>
them, as if they waited to ſee when the players would come foorth vppon the ſtage, or elſe the good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes go to the ale-houſe (where now &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they find their miniſter drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his morning draught before he go to his ſeruice) to drink a pot or two of nappy ale, that thereby they may the better hold out the ſeruice time; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which ſpace they ſtand gazing &amp; ſtaring vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Miniſter, as a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie clowne which neuer was in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don before, doth gaze when he goeth downe <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> at the Gold-ſmithes ſtauls, or els they ſtare one vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like as theeues do when they are taken in a robery, or els ſome of them walke without in the warme ſonne, &amp; make theyr bargaines, and generallie you doe ſee no more deuotion there, then you doe in a Faire or Market; no man nor woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaying one praier, but all waiting for (that which they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue in that ſtate) <hi>the peace of God.</hi> The which being haſtely chopped vp, they ruſh and guſh out of the Church as water doth out of a mill pole, when
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:13600:72"/>
the flood yeates are ſodainely plucked vp, no man moouing lip, or legge, but ſtriuing vvho ſhall be ſooneſt at his pottage. Neither doe they vſe any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to their Miniſter, no nor yet to his wife, but account of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as they are indeed) moſt abiect perſons. And no meruaile, when as their ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, whom they tearme Biſhops, are little eſteemed of among their Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſanes, &amp; eſpecially among Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; are leaſt accounted of among Barrons, and other Noble men, vvho diſdaine their companie, &amp; contemne their preſence: whereas amongſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, Prieſts haue euer bin great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie reuerenced, Biſhoppes and Prelats highly honoured, &amp; all Cleargie men much eſteemed, and theyr companie &amp; preſence, of all ſorts deſired, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently accepted of. The ſame reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reſpect haue Catholikes euer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in ſpeaking, &amp; in making men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods Books, Angels, Saints, or of ſuch like holy things: for ſpeaking of ſuch they vſually ſay: <hi>The holie Bible,</hi> or <hi>the holie Scriptures, the holie Ghospell, the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:13600:72"/>
bleſſed Sacrament, the holie Sacraments &amp;c.</hi> And of Angels &amp; Saints: <hi>the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, S. Michael, S Gabriel, &amp;c.</hi> And the French more reuerentlie vſe to ſay: <hi>Mounſieur S. Michael, Mounſieur S. Pierre, &amp;c. Our bleſſed Lady,</hi> or <hi>the holie virgin S. Marie,</hi> or <hi>the mother of God, S. Peeter, S. Paul, S. Amb. S. Auguſt. S. Greg. S Hierome, S. Bernard, &amp;c.</hi> and generally in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Holie thinges, they vſe Holie tearmes: But the Proteſtants ſhew as little reuerence &amp; deuotion in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as they doe in dooing: for they ſpeake no more reuerentlie of ſuch, then they do of the prophaneſt things they haue. They tearme all, as if they vvere in <hi>puris natalibus: The Bible, the Word, the Testament, the Communion book, Baptiſme, Bread, the Supper, Angels, Mich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, Gabriel, Peter, Paul, Marie, or Marie the virgin, Ambroſe, Auſten, Gregorie the Pope, Hierome the monke, Bernard the Abot, &amp;c.</hi> with as great inciuilitie, irreuerence, and want of good manners, as if rude Countriemen in talking of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Nobles ſhould ſay; <hi>the Keeper, the Treaſurer, the Admirall, Eſſex, Southampt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:13600:73"/>
Monioy, &amp;c.</hi> or inſteede of naming men of worſhippe by their Chriſtian names ſhuld ſay: <hi>Tom, Dick, Wil, Robin, Iacke, Hodge, &amp;c.</hi> Which diuerſitie of dealing when I conſidered it with my ſelfe, I could not but think, &amp; deeme the Proteſtants profeſsion voide of all impreſsion of pietie and deuotion; &amp; contrariwiſe in the Catholike Church to be all ſincere affection, and celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all humilitie towards almightie God, and towards al things appropriated to his ſeruice, as alſo towards thoſe, who are the greateſt partakers of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie fauour.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="reason">
            <head>THE XXIII. REASON. Reſembling in Doctrine, and deedes, old Heretikes.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Irenaeus l. 1. cap. 20. Theo lib. 1. Haeretic. fab. Aug. hereſ. 54. Hiſt. trip. l. 8. cap. 9.</note>I HAVE conferred the Doctrine, deedes, &amp; manners of Proteſtants, with thoſe of the old Heretikes long ſince condemned by the Catholicke Church, &amp; I find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> little or nothing at all to differ: for as touching Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the proteſtants hold with <hi>Simon
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:13600:73"/>
Magus</hi> that good workes are not meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious: they renounce the Pope with <hi>Nouatus:</hi> they refuſe to faſte on ſuch dayes as the Church hath preſcribed,<note place="margin">Hierom in prae. in dia. aduer. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. Aug. de her. cap 45. Epiph. l 3 her 75 Hier. lib. 1. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Iouin. idem coa. vigilant. ad Exuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> and denie free-wil with the <hi>Manichees:</hi> they denie ſacrifice, and praier for the dead with <hi>Aeriu:</hi> with <hi>Iouinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> they put no differences of ſins, nor make virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity any better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mariage: they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no tapers, nor lights in their chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, &amp; they ſpeak againſt worſhiping of Saints, and deſpiſe holie reliques of bleſſed Martyrs with <hi>Vigilantiu:</hi> they take away the oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacrifice, &amp; the hallowing of Chriſme with <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyches:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo Epiſt. 75. Aug. hereſ 88. &amp; de pec. merit. lib. 3. cap. 5. loa. Shut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. 50. cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarum cap. 18.</note> they teach that childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be ſaued without baptiſme, &amp; therefore that it is not of neceſsitie with the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians:</hi> they bragge with the <hi>Donatiſtes</hi> that all the world hath ſwarued from the right faith, and they onely are the true Church. And all the reſt of theyr doctrine in a maner is borrowed thus of old heretiks, which here particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſet downe my breuity will not permit. The like cobaerence &amp; agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they haue with the old heretikes
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:13600:74"/>
in deeds &amp; maners: for I haue found by experience that the Proteſtant preachers expect,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. 7. Hiſt. c. 26.</note> and deſire great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of their hearers, as <hi>Paulus Samo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatenus</hi> did of his followers; they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Aultars,<note place="margin">Opt. lib. 6 contr. Do.</note> abuſe the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, handle deſpitefullie Holie Chriſme, as the <hi>Donatiſtes</hi> did; they faigne cauſes, and come excuſes why they will not goe to Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 3. con. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Gram mat. ca. 45. &amp; hiſt. trip lib. 5. c. 34.</note> as the ſaide <hi>Donatiſtes, Macedonius,</hi> and <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> did. The <hi>Donatiſtes</hi> alſo fained that diuers Biſhops vvho were abſent, and that one who was dead did take theyr part againſt Catholickes, therby to make theyr nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to ſeeme greater: and there in <hi>England,</hi> vvhen not ſomuch as one Catholicke Biſhop could be induced by any perſwations, promiſes, gifts, or honours, to conſent to their Proteſtancy, yet were not the Proteſtantes aſhamed to abuſe the Queenes Highneſſe vvith this fained Supplication:<note place="margin">Anno. 1. Reginae E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabethae.</note> 
               <hi>Moſt humblie beſeech your moſt excellent Maiestie, your faithfull and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient Subiects, the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, &amp;c.</hi> The ſame <hi>Donatiſtes,</hi> did
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:13600:74"/>
torment moſte cruellie Catholicke Prieſts, plucking out the eyes of ſome,<note place="margin">Aug. Pon. com. Epiſt. 50.</note> and of one Biſhoppe they cut out the tongue, and hand, and murdered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. And the Proteſtantes of late in Fraunce did the like to Catholicke Prieſts, and beſides tying haulters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their neckes, they drewe them diſpiteouſlie after theyr horſes, that done, they cut off theyr eares, noſes, &amp; priuie partes, they ware their eares in their hats inſteed of brooches, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally they either hanged vp their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes,<note place="margin">Claud. de Sanctis in lib. du Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t des eglyſes.</note> or elſe ſhot them through with Piſtolles: of others they hackled and mangled their faces: of otherſome to trie force &amp; ſtrength, they did cleaue in two at one ſtroke their heades: and of an old Religious man at <hi>Mans,</hi> they firſt cut off his priuie parts, then they fried them, after they forced him to ſwallow them downe, and laſt of all they did rip his ſtomake; being yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, and ſee what was become there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. At <hi>S. Macharius</hi> they buried the Catholikes quicke, they cut Infants in two, they ripped the bellies of Prieſts,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:13600:75"/>
and drew out their intrals by little &amp; little, winding them about a ſticke, or tree. At <hi>Patte</hi> a village, ſome 6. leages from <hi>Orleaunce,</hi> they burned Catholiks &amp; threw infants into the fire there to periſh with the reſt. And manie other like outrages, and barbarous cruelties they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittd, which who ſo deſireth to know,<note place="margin">Victor de perſec. va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>- l. 1. cap. 3. &amp; l 1. cap. de offic. praef. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor lib. 3, Epiſc. Egip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti Epiſt. ad Marcum Papaem.</note> may find them ſet downe by <hi>Claudius de Saintes</hi> in his booke noted before i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the margent. The <hi>Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes troadeth B. Sacrament vnder their feet, they ouerthrew the church<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es in <hi>Africa,</hi> &amp; made of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtables for their horſes, of Altars clothes, &amp; veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they made ſhirts and breeches, they burned the bookes, and carried the ornaments of the Churches away. And how the Proteſtants haue abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the B. Sacrament, ſpoiled church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, burned bookes, and haue not onlie made breeches, ſhirts, &amp; cuſhions, but euen coats for players, &amp; dizzardes of holy veſtments, &amp; Aultar clothes, you cannot but know.<note place="margin">Theod. lib 1. cap. 6</note> 
               <hi>Iulian</hi> that wicked Aapoſtata, robbed Churches, ſpoiled the Cleargy of their priuiledges, bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:13600:75"/>
the Prieſtes, ouerthrew Aultars, cauſed the ſacrifice to ceaſe, reproued the Chriſtians for doing reuerence to the Croſſe,<note place="margin">Cyrill lib. 6. contra Iulian. &amp; l. 10 coa. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undem.</note> and for making the ſigne thereof in their foreheades, for paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it vpon the dores of theyr houſes, and for worſhipping the Reliques of Mattyrs, for viſiting their tombes, for praying to them at theyr graues,<note place="margin">Zozom. li. 5. cap 12.</note> and Sepulchres, and termed them <hi>deadme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> hee ouerthrew &amp; deſtroyed the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; pictures of Chriſt, he brake o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, wherein the bones of S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> vvere religiouſlie kept,<note place="margin">Theod. lib 5. cap. 6.</note> burned them, &amp; diſperſed abroad the aſhes. Now whether the Proteſtants haue iumped iuſt into the ſteps of this wicked Apoſtata in doing the like or no? I leaue to your iudgement, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp; conſideration.<note place="margin">Zozom li. 5. cap 21 Athan. lib. de paſſion. imag. Chr.</note> The <hi>Panims</hi> or heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men brake the image of chriſt: the Iewes crucified it, as theyr Elders had done Chriſt himſelfe: the Iew in in whoſe houſe it was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, was troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for it, &amp; brought before the high prieſt, for that he ſeemed by keeping that picture, that hee was a Chriſtian.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:13600:76"/>
And doe not the Proteſtants euen as the Heathens and Iewes did? The Iew was thought to be a fauourer of Chriſt, becauſe he kept his picture in his houſe: and why ſhould not Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes by the like reaſon, be iudged fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers, and louers of Chriſt, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his Image in theyr Churches, houſes, and chambers? Or why ſhould not Proteſtantes be deemed aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and enimies to Chriſt, as the Iews and Heathens were, ſeeing they can no more endure his Picture or Croſſe then they could? The old Heretikes, as <hi>Neſtorius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. lib. 7. hiſt. cap. 23. Euſ. lib 6. cap. 55. &amp; lib. 7. c. 24. Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor. lib. 6 cap. 30. Theodor. lib. 1. cap. 4</note> 
               <hi>Nouatus, Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> the <hi>Arrians</hi> &amp; others were out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure proud, arrogant, and wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conceited of themſelues, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Doctours of the Church, which had writttn before them, and preferring them-ſelues before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whatſoeuer: the verie ſame doe the Proteſtants in a moſt proude, and arrogant manner, and the ringleader, and Father of them all is not aſhamed to breake out into theſe ſpeeches:<note place="margin">Lutherus col. menſ.</note> 
               <hi>I haue Excommunicated Origine long agoe,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:13600:76"/>
there is nothing ſinguler in Athanaſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">fol. 474. &amp; 460. &amp; 932. &amp; 476 &amp; 477. &amp; 17.</note> 
               <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian is very ſuperstitious: I make no count of Chriſostome, for he is but a pratler: Baſil plainely is nothing worth, hee is altogether a Monke: Cyprian the Martyr is a weake Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiner: Hierome ought not to be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Doctours of the Church, for he was an Heretike: amongst all the Doctors ſcarſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie one, except Augustine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. ger. fol. 443. &amp; 449.</note> 
               <hi>vnderstood what the ſpirit &amp; the letter were: in all theyr books there is great darkeneſſe of Faith: Gregories Sermons are not worth a deafe nut, the diuell deceaued him groſſelie in his Dialogues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus doe they cenſure the auncient Fathers, but of themſelues they ſpeak farre otherwiſe: for the ſame Arch-Proteſtant ſaith that hee himſelfe is <hi>a faithfull Prophet, an Apostle, an Euangelist,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom 2. Ger fol. 522. &amp; fol 79. Tom. 3. f. 334. Coll. menſ. fol. 488.</note> 
               <hi>a liuing Saint, &amp;c.</hi> And further he ſaid of himſelfe, that hee is <hi>Eſay the Prophet, &amp; Phillip Melanctho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ieremie.</hi> Was there euer any <hi>Thraſo</hi> ſo impudent, as thus to bragge of him-ſelfe. And yet his followers were not aſhamed to extoll and praiſe him in ſuch ſort, as I cannot without ſhame and offence to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an eares declare the ſame: but yet to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:13600:77"/>
giue you a little taſte thereof, I vvill here ſet downe a diſtichon, which his Diſciples made in praiſe of him,<note place="margin">In parte contra Ste<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phanum Agricolam ca. 4. b. 9. a.</note> and which <hi>Cyriacus Spangenbergius</hi> one of his principall followers ſtoutlie maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be true, and allowable the diſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chon is this.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Christ is habet primas,</l>
               <l>habeas tibi Paule ſecundus,</l>
               <l>Ast loca poſt illos</l>
               <l>proxima, Luther habet.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="¶" place="margin">Which thus maie bee Engli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note>The chiefe of all is Chriſt himſelfe,</l>
               <l>the next is Paul by grace,</l>
               <l>Backe Saints, Apoſtles, Angels all</l>
               <l>for next is Luthers place.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Col. menſ. fol. 159.</note>And <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf in another place coupleth himſelfe with the ſame holie Apoſtle <hi>Saint Paule:</hi> But to ſee vvhat ſtaffe his adhaerentes vſe in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and praiſe, is too redicu-to behold,<note place="margin">Col. menſ. ger fo. 354 &amp; 159. &amp; Beza in lib Icom r 4. a &amp; in praef. in nouum teſt. f. 144. a. &amp; Luth. in praefati. in comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Phill. in Epiſt. ad Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. p. 2. &amp; tom 2. Ien. fol. 79. &amp; in li. coa. rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ang. &amp; to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. f. 119 &amp; col. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. f. 144. &amp; f. 474 &amp; to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. Lat. Wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten. f 457. &amp; in l. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eruoarbit. &amp; Stigel. l. 2. Poemat. n. 4. Amſd. deſc. Luth. &amp; Ab. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Carola. an. l. 7. b. Euſ. l. 7. cap. 24 Soc. li. 6. c. 8. Zozo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. li. 8. c. 8. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cph. l. c. 16. idem li. 11. cap: 12. Tertul. in lib. de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer aduerſ. herſ. Epip: her: 49. &amp; 79: Aug: her: 27: Hieron: ad Eteſiph: aduerſ. pelagianos: Euſeb</note> which you may ſee at large in their writings, and thus they do not only write of their maſter &amp; captaine, but euen one of another and of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in a moſt ſhameful &amp; lying ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner.</p>
            <p>They follow alſo the faſhion of old heretiks in that they diſagre ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:13600:77"/>
in Doctrine, &amp; are ſo contentious, &amp; doe affect &amp; ſeek after eloquence, and ſmooth ſpeeches, more than after the truth, as they did. And neuer any Arch-heretike among them is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as there neuer was in the auncient time: for that their ſin was ouer hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, &amp; againſt the Holy Ghoſt; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe they put any difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Eccleſiaſticall perſons and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, as they old heretiks did not. And they ſeaſon their errours with ſonges, &amp; ballades in the vulgar tongue, to the end that the common people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting to heare and ſinge them, might thereby ſucke theyr errours, as you ſee them doe by the Geneua Pſalmes, which women, children, and all ſorts confuſedlie ſing, &amp; ſo did the old heretiks, as hiſtoriographers make mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The women among the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes in times paſt were ſo ſhameles, &amp; malapert, that they tooke vpon them to diſpute, and to reaſon of matters of religion: &amp; they helped foreward the Hereſie, by teaching, preaching, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, wra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gling, iangling, prophecying,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:13600:78"/>
and by all meanes poſsible.<note place="margin">5.</note> And doe not,<note place="margin">p. 14. Niceph. l. cap. 22. Tom 1. Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ger. f. 336 &amp; f. 17. &amp; 341.</note> I pray you, the women amongeſt the Proteſtantes the like, following therin their Father <hi>Luthers</hi> aduiſe, who licenſeth them to doe ſuch thinges, &amp; namely to preach?</p>
            <p>The olde Heretikes were verie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiue, and deſirous to heare of the ſinnes, and faults of Prieſts, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſticall perſons,<note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt 137.</note> and when they heard any ſuch, they greatlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced thereat, and blazed it abroad with great exaggerations, and additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and doe not the Proteſtants the ſame? Yea it were more ſufferable if they blazed abroade onelie thinges which were true: but they moſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlie faine, &amp; make vpon their own fingers the greateſt part of ſuch tales as are tolde of Eccleſiaſticall perſons. Wherein they ſhewe how farre they are from the ſpirit and minde of that moſt Religious Emperour <hi>Constantine</hi> the great,<note place="margin">Zozom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> li. 1. cap 6. Niceph. li. 8. cap. 16.</note> who would not in any wiſe heare the faults of Biſhops &amp; Prieſts, but affirmed that if he ſhould chaunce to finde ſuch an one violating wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:13600:78"/>
hee would couer him with his purple cloake, for feare of ſcandale.</p>
            <p>I could heere alleadge manie moe things both of doctrine and manners, in which the Heretikes of old, and the Proteſtants of theſe dayes, doe agree, and iumpe togeather, and becauſe of breuitie I will ſurceaſe, praying you warily to weigh whoſe ſteps you tread in, and whoſe examples you follow.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="reason">
            <head>THE XXIIII. REASON. Peace and tranquilitie.</head>
            <p>THE Catholike Romane religion (according to the prophecies of the old Teſtament) began with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, mildnes, and with all quiet, and peaceable meanes, by which it alſo encreaſed, and dilated it ſelfe: the teachers, and profeſſours thereof, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all patience and humilitie, but neuer any violence, or force in the planting thereof; whereas the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants both haue begun, and holde on theyr courſe vvith ſeditious tumults, wars, cruelties, and other outragious Tragedies: as vvith ouerthrowing
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:13600:79"/>
noble families, making away honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſonages, &amp; with deſtroying all before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where they ſet foot, as <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> where they bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, can ſufficiently witnes, where were ſlaine within one yeere by rebellion &amp; war for this new religion,<note place="margin">Sled<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</note> aboue one hundred thouſand people, country-men taking armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Lords, &amp; ſubiectes againſt their Princes for the ſame. And what rule, and reuell they haue kept about their Goſpell in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> &amp; in <hi>Denmarke,</hi> is wel known where they haue gathered ſundry armies, pitched many campes, fought many battailes, made many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, deſtroyed Countries, Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Townes, Villages, cauſed ſuch ſlaughter, and hauocke of Chriſtian blood as euery man abhorreth to hear of. And what tragedies I praye you haue they raiſed in <hi>Scotlande?</hi> Haue they not murdered their Princes, and ouerthrowne Noble houſes, and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, as the houſes and Lynages of <hi>Hamiltons,</hi> of <hi>Duglaſſes,</hi> of <hi>Stewardes,</hi> and of others? Neither hath <hi>Ireland</hi> eſcaped
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:13600:79"/>
ſcot free. But to ſpeake of our owne Countrye, I cannot without teares re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſommarily the troubles, calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; vtter ruines of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble families, honorable &amp; worſhipfull perſonages, &amp; of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth it ſelfe cauſed by the Proteſtants, or for the controuerſie of religion In <hi>k. Henry</hi> the 8. his time, two, the chiefeſt of the whole Realme, for vertue &amp; learning were put to death, with great numbers of others, both ſpiritual &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall, &amp; many noble families were quite ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne. King <hi>Edward</hi> being crowned King: new Lordes, new Earles, new Marquiſes, and new Dukes tooke the places of the old: new fellowes were called out of <hi>Germany,</hi> to witte, <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> two Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taes Fryars, waited on by two Fuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lugge vvenches, vvhich had beene Nunnes, vvho came to teache a new religion: but with expreſſe condition to be indifferent to teach vvhat ſect, or opinions, eyther of LVTHER, ZVVINGLIVS, or CALVINE, or of anye other vvhatſoeuer, vvhich the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:13600:80"/>
Parliament then in gathering ſhoulde agree vpon. The poore irreligious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtataes with their ſacrilegious laſſes were content ſo to doe, and vpon that condition they were ſent, the one to <hi>Oxforde</hi> with his wench at his taile, and the other to <hi>Cambridge</hi> accompanied with his laſſe. Then might you haue ſeene iolly holding &amp; drawing about Religion, placing, and diſplacing, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, and ſetting at liberty, all men forced to ſweare to a forme of ſeruice drawen out in haſt by certaine of the L. Protectours chaplaines, (which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice was neuer heard of in the worlde before) but the Cleargie refuſed ſo to doe, and therefore were depriued, and impriſoned. The Duke of <hi>Somerſet</hi> was head, and ruler of the newe deuiſed Church, (for the Childe-King, was a playing him, &amp; could not once thinke of any ſuch thing) and attended to his owne aduauncement by purchaſing good olde land, whileſt the two ſillye Apoſtataes kept the people occupied with newe doctrine, and with not tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of him. And then began ſuch
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:13600:80"/>
reuell, and hold, and tye in the lande, as that the Protector firſt of all cut off the head of his brother the Admirall: the Earle of <hi>Warwicke</hi> beheaded the Protector, and diuers others of his friendes, making him-ſelfe Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and complotting with the Duke of <hi>Suffolke</hi> to cut off all king <hi>Henries</hi> children, &amp; to bring in <hi>Suffolkes</hi> daughter, and <hi>Northumberlands</hi> ſonne as they did: for the which both theyr heades were afterwardes cutt off by Queene <hi>Marie.</hi> And in her Maieſties time, that nowe is, all the Sacred Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were depriued in one day, &amp; al, or the moſt of them impriſoned du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theyr liues. Manie noble houſes abuſed, &amp; diſgraced, and diuers ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, manie both of honour and worſhipp intollerably afflicted, manie thouſands of inferiour ſort greiuouſly perſecuted, aboue an hundred Prieſts tortured, hanged, and quartered, the moſte of them beeing Gentlemen of worſhipfull diſcent, of rare witt, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and of other parts incomperable. The Realme is deuided, and ſhiuered
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:13600:81"/>
into a thouſand peeces, the old friends and allies thereof, made enimies to it, new friends few and weake, the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inhabitants moſt pittifullie deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded amongſt themſelues at home, &amp; toſſed and turmoiled abroade, euerie man of what ſtate, conditon, or religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoeuer he be of, hath felt the ſmart of this new Ghoſpell, eyther in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in his friendes, children, ſeruants, kinſfolkes, goodes, honoures, &amp; moſt of all the Realme, and Common-weale in it ſelfe, vvith ten thouſand other troubles, and afflictions, vvhich the Proteſtantes Religion carrieth vvith it, wheather ſoeuer it goeth. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer expelling &amp; driuing away Peace, and Tranquilitie, vvhich finde har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and entertainement only in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike realmes, and common-weales. When I weighed, and conſidered theſe things diligently with my ſelfe, I could not but diſlike your new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, euer accompanied vvith Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, Inſurrections, Ruines, Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and vvith all manner of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall miſeries, as is afore-ſaide, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:13600:81"/>
cleaue vnto the olde Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, euer bringing with it peace, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, loue friendſhipp, plentie, and all kinde of happineſſe, as wee ſee in Lands &amp; Countries which euer haue kept the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="reason">
            <head>THE XXV. REASON. All kind of witneſſes againſt one and that onely in ſhow, or in very deed none at all.</head>
            <p>EVERIE man knoweth that the Proteſtants can bring foorth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to witneſſe theyr religion, but onely the Scriptures, and how they make for them, I haue partlie ſhewed before: for in euerie deed they being rightly examined, &amp; truely interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beare witneſſe moſte of all other thinges againſt them: for out of all doubt, Gods word is not contrarie, but moſt conſonant to all thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aleaged, &amp; practiſed through the whole chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> world for ſo many ages together. And wheras they wil admit
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:13600:82"/>
no expoſitors of holie Scriptures, but the Scriptures themſelues: for that (as they ſay) one place expoundeth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; I aske the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then, how their chiefe maiſter <hi>M. Luther,</hi> when as hee would moſte gladlie haue denyed the <hi>Reall Preſence,</hi> thinking thereby to wreake his teene the more on the Pope, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that he could not do it, becauſe the words were ſo manifeſt for it? And why hath that text beene ſo toſſed &amp; wreſted in this age, as that ſundry ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries haue wringed out of it, aboue foure-ſcore different opinions, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; and yet euerie one defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with tooth and naile his interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to be ſound, and right? So that in fine they haue no witneſſe at all of their new inuented doctrine, but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one his priuate fancie, or conceite: whereas the Catholike Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all the reaſons before alleadged, hath all thinges in the world witneſſes of it: for if you looke vpp to Heauen, you may there ſee amongſt innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Martyrs, vvhich all gaue theyr liues for the ſaide Religion, three and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:13600:82"/>
thirtie which were Popes of Rome. And to ſpeake ſome what in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Smyr.</note> the zealous Martyr <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> who in Eccleſiaſticall affaires would haue no man, no not the King equall to a Biſhop, and who wrote Apoſtolicall traditions, which hee him-ſelfe had ſeene, ſealed his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his blood.<note place="margin">Lib. 3. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> who declared the true Faith by ſucceſsion in the See of Rome was of this religion. <hi>S. Victor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. 5. hiſt. 24 Euſeb. 4. hiſt. 14.</note> who by his po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall power, kept in ſubiection all <hi>Africke,</hi> was of this religion. <hi>S. Polycarpe</hi> who went to <hi>Rome</hi> about the queſtion of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> was of this religion. <hi>S. Cyprian, S. Sixtus, S. Laurence,</hi> vvith infinite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, both Doctours and Saintes doe witneſſe the Roman Religion. Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes of Virgins, which defended their virginitie againſt diuels, &amp; men,<note place="margin">Euſeb. 8. hiſt. 17. Aug l. 9. conf. cap. 7. vſ. ad 3.</note> were of this religion. <hi>Saint Helen,</hi> who went to Ieruſalem, to finde out the Croſſe of our Sauiour was of this reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The mother of <hi>S. Austin. S. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica,</hi> who at her death requeſted that ſhe might haue Maſſe ſaid for her, &amp; to be prayed for, was out of all doubt
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:13600:83"/>
a Papiſt: So were <hi>S. Paul</hi> the Eremite, <hi>S. Hilarion, S. Anthonie, S. Nicolas, S. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, S. Benet,</hi> with millions of ſuch like, who were fed with faſting, cloathed with ſacke-cloath, and enriched vvith all maner of vertues. And to be ſhort, were there, I pray you, any Saintes in heauen, before this our age, vvhich were not Papiſt? I am ſure that either heauen was empty vntil <hi>Luth.</hi> ſhooke of his hood, or if there were any there they were Papiſts.</p>
            <p>Now if you looke downe into hell, you may behold the Heathen perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, Iewes, Turkes, and Heretikes, in perpetuall tormentes for perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and ſtriuing againſt the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke ROMAN CHVRCH To this <hi>Constantine</hi> the great brought peace, and quietneſſe. In this Church there hath beene continuall ſucceſsion of Biſhops without any interruption. All Biſhopps and Paſtours of particular Churches, in what land or country ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they were in vnder the cope of heauen, were me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of this Church. As for example, <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> at <hi>Antioch,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:13600:83"/>
Peter, Alexander, Athanaſius, Theophilus,</hi> at <hi>Alexandria: Macharius,</hi> and <hi>Cyrillus</hi> at <hi>Ieruſalem: Proclus</hi> at <hi>Constantinople: Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> in <hi>Cappadocia: Thauma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgus</hi> in <hi>Pontus: Polycarpas</hi> at <hi>Smyrna: Iustinus</hi> at <hi>Athens: Dyoniſius</hi> at <hi>Corinth: Gregory</hi> at <hi>Nyſa, Methodius</hi> at <hi>Tyrus, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phreem</hi> in <hi>Syria, Cyprian, Optatus, Austin</hi> in <hi>Africke, Epiphanius</hi> in <hi>Cyprus, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Paulinus, Gaudentius, Prosper, Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus, Vigilius</hi> in <hi>Italy, Irenaeus, Martine, Hylarius, Eucherius, Gregory, Saluianus</hi> in <hi>Fraunce: Vincentius, Orotius, Hildefonſus, Leander, Iſidorus,</hi> in <hi>Spayne, Fugatius, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianus, Iustus, Melytus, Beda</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> were Biſhoppes and Paſtours of this Church. In briefe, whatſoeuer deedes or works, ſignes or monuments, frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or reliques remaine yet in anie land or countrie of them, who planted the Chriſtian Faith there, doe teſtifie the Catholike Roman Religion. All Princes, Kings, &amp; Emperors, all States and commonweales which euer were chriſtened: the <hi>Theodoſians</hi> in the eaſt, the <hi>Charles</hi> in the weſt, the <hi>Edwards</hi> in Englande, the <hi>Leweſſes</hi> in Fraunce,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:13600:84"/>
the <hi>Hermigildes</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Henries</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi> the <hi>Wenceſlaes</hi> in <hi>Boeme-Lande,</hi> the <hi>Leopoldes,</hi> in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the <hi>Steeuens</hi> in <hi>Hungary,</hi> the <hi>Ioſophates</hi> in <hi>India</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and protected the Roman Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, they builded Churches, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded religious houſes, &amp; erected many other Monuments of pietie, not for Proteſtants Iwis, but for the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of the Catholike Roman Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which Faith and Religion <hi>S. Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricke</hi> brought firſt into <hi>Ireland, Palladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> into <hi>Scotland, S. Augustine</hi> into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and other Apoſtles into other countries: witneſſes of this Religion are al Vniuerſities, Colledges, Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, Monaſteries, Churches, Chappels and innumerable other monumentes: Witneſſes their foundations, their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, yea and the very buildings themſelues: witneſſes all Reueſtryes, Chauncels with ſteppes vp, Aultars, Rood lofts, Croſſ-buildings, al Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Church and Church-yeardes, Market-places, and High-waies: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes all Biſhoprickes, Deaneries, Arch-deaconries, Prebendes, Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:13600:84"/>
Vicariages, &amp; ſuch like, ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned trow you, for women, &amp; children to make them gentles? Witneſſes all tithes, and other liuely-hoods ſo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly lotted out, not for miniſters wenches, &amp; their brats, but for Sacred anoynted Prieſts. Good Lord, what would the founders of all theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes ſay, if they might come but to ſee how their lands and goods, which they ſo religiouſlie beſtowed to honor God withall, are by Proteſtants em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed? Witneſſes ſpirituall Courtes, Viſitations, Conuocations, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, &amp; Suſpenſions: witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes probations of dead mens wils: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes bidding and forbidding of ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: witneſſes partitions of Dioceſe &amp; pariſhes; all ordeyned, and inſtituted by Papiſts. Witneſſes auncient lawes and cuſtomes: witneſſes the vulgar manners of people, the Election, and Inauguration of Emperours, the rites of annoynting &amp; crowning of kings, the dubbing of knights, &amp;c. witneſſes coynes, windows, towne-gates, town-houſes, all rules, and to conclude, all
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:13600:85"/>
things in the world witnes the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Roman Religion.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I briefelie my deare frendes ſet downe ſome plaine reaſons of the religion which I profeſſe, &amp; for the enioying of which, I am content to forgoe my natiue ſoyle, my deare Parents, you my deareſt friends, with all the reſt, and all thoſe commodities and pleaſures, which you account in your letter. I wiſh you not to thinke euill of mee for ſo doing, for it is the religion wherein I was borne, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and confirmed: it is the religion which from time to time hath bin v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſallie receaued throughout all Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome: it is the religion which there in our own countrie of al others is the firſt, the auncienteſt, the moſte benificiall of all the reſt, the mother, and begetter of the others, &amp; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of all our Chriſtian Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and therefore beare with me I pray you, in that I will not yeelde vp my title, and intereſt of that which I haue receaued from myne Elders, by lineall and lawful diſcent, no man for
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:13600:85"/>
theſe thouſand yeares at the leaſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to put mee, or any of my prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors out of it. Yet if any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant or other whatſoeuer, can ſhew me any good euidence, why I ſhould not poſſeſſe the ſame, I am readie to giue it vp: but hitherto they promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and vaunting to ſhew good eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, haue brought forth nothing but words, and forgerie. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by Gods grace, I purpoſe to hold the ſame, euen vntill my dying day, except ſuch euidence come againſt my title, as is not to be ſhewed, no not by an Angell, if he ſhould come from heauen. God bleſſe you in the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his mercie, who ſende vs ioyfull meeting, eyther in this world, or in the next, or in both.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13600:86"/>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:13600:86"/>
            <head>A COPIE OF ANOTHER LETTER WHICH THE TWO Cittizens of London wrote to <hi>theyr friende beyond the Seas, ſhortlie after that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ſent.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EARE AND WEL-beloued friend, after that we had ſent the laſt Letter dated the <hi>13.</hi> of September Anno. <hi>1599.</hi> wee conſulting, and weighing the contents thereof, with ſome what more deepe conſiderations then before wee had done: it was thought good to write vnto you this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Letter, to let you vnderstand that wee will not receaue, nor medle with any grounds or reaſons of your faith and religion, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you neede not to trouble your ſelfe with writing any: for wee aſſure our ſelues that you can bring forth none, but ſuch as Papiſtes
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:13600:87"/>
vſe to alleadge, which are now growne verie ſtale, &amp; out of requeſt. Onlie this is the deſire of vs al, that you would returne without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay: but yet ſo, as you may ſhew your ſelfe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to her Ma. lawes in comming to the Church as other good dutiful ſubiects doe: for ſurelie what Religion ſoeuer you profeſſe, we thinke you may with ſafe conſcience come to heare Diuine Seruice, or a Sermon, beeing no further vrged, but that you may thinke, and pray as you liſt. And what Scripture, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or reaſon can you ſhew, or pretend for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing ſo to doe? For we knowe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, which women, &amp; ſuch ſillie ſoules are accuſtomed to make in ſaying: It is againſt my conſcience, I may not with a ſafe conſcience ſo doe: is too fooliſh for you, who ſeeme to haue more knowledge. Wee ſuppoſed at the first, that your refuſall proceeded of a timerous &amp; ouer ſcrupulous conſcience, but now wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to ſuſpect, that becauſe you haue gone ſo far in that courſe, you thinke it would be ſome diſcredite, as to be deemed vnconstant, and a turne-coate, if you ſhould in any ſort relent, and come to conformitie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you minde ſtill to be obſtinate: but wee friendly aduiſe you to beware of ſuch pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhnes,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:13600:87"/>
proceeding indeede from the roote of pride, &amp; we wiſh you to ſubmit your ſelfe to your gracious Princeſſe, her honourable Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, &amp; to the lawes of your natiue Country, and weigh with your ſelfe, what you are to ſtand againſt a whole Realme, and wee ſee no reaſon, but that you may as well come to Church, as you did once (if wee be not decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) eate vpon ſome occaſion, fleſh vpon a fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, a thing ſo oppoſite to your religion. If you can maiſter your minde, ſo as you may come home in this ſort, we ſhall be all moſt glad of you: for if you do, neyther Parents nor frends will entertaine you, nor ſpeake one worde in your cauſe, for if they ſhould it were but in vaine, &amp; beſides might bring them into ſome ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; diſcredit. God giue you grace to be wiſe in time, for if you holde on in this your wilfull follie, wee feare much, that you who ſhuld haue bin moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to your friends, wil become their greateſt greefe, &amp; giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to wiſh that you neuer had bin borne: whereas being tractable in this our requeſt, you may ſalue all ſores paſt, benefit your ſelf, pleaſure many, do great good in your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, comfort your kinsfolkes, proue your ſelfe wiſe in deed, gaine credit amongst the beſt, and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:13600:88"/>
liue pleaſantly manie an yeare. Which thing your Parents, and wee moſt earnestlie deſire to ſee. And thus, they with paternall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges, and wee all ioyntlie with millions of commendations, commit you to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. London this <hi>2.</hi> of October. an. <hi>1599.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt kinde and louing friendes. R. and G.H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:13600:88"/>
            <head>AN AVNSWERE TO THE LETTER AFORE GOING.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST louing frindes, I had writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reaſons of Religion before I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the countermaunde in your laſt letter, which came to my handes very late, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dated the 2. of <hi>October Anno</hi> 1599. it came not to me vntill the 20. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> of the ſame yeere. Peruſing the ſame, &amp; weighing the contents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I find that you little care what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion I reteine in my minde and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſo that I be conformable to the Lawes of our Country, in hearing Seruice, as it is nowe ſet forth, or a peece of a Sermon, as it is nowe there
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:13600:89"/>
preached. Manye circumſtances and ſurmiſes you vſe, but all driue to the finall ſcope by you intended, which is to driue me to your Church. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede as worldly friends, for an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall kinde of ſuch loue towardes me, you labour very much, for the which I hartely thanke you, but alaſle your counſell and deſire is no other than S. <hi>Peters</hi> was to our Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> or thoſe pittifull frinds was to <hi>Eleazarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Mac. 6.</note> for you builde all vpon our preſent ſafety, &amp; welfare in this world. And if I thought that I might followe your counſell, &amp; neuertheleſſe ſaue my ſoule, ſurelye then I were the moſt miſerable foole that euer was in the worlde, if I would not ſo doe For to ſpeake of my fellow Catholikes in <hi>England,</hi> as well as of my ſelfe, can there I pray you anye man be more madde, than to ſuffer loſſe of goods, and liuing, to bee diſcredited, contemned, and troden vnder euery mans foote that liſteth to ſpoile them, to lie in priſon, in dungeons, to be rac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, reracked, hanged, bowelled aliue and boyled, and after all this, to goe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:13600:89"/>
to hell, there to bee tormented eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallye with Fire and Brimſtone, and all for Religion, when-as beeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Lawes of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: in going to Church, they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy liuings, liberties, &amp; liues, feede at large, and liue gallantly, alofte in all delicacy, mirth, paſtime, &amp; pleaſure in this world, &amp; after all this, in the ende to be ſure of ioy in the next. If you coulde proue this to me, then I ſaye, you might condemne mee for the wretchedſt miſcreant that euer liued, if I did not yeelde to your aduice and deſire. But vntil you can proue it, I hope you will conſter my courſe in charitable maner, and iudge better of me, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I do it of obſtinacy, or for feare of diſcredit, or for anye worldly reſpecte, for I cal God Almighty (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whome we are ſure to meete one daye, and to receiue according to our thoughts, words, &amp; deeds) to witneſſe that I doe refraine &amp; refuſe to goe to your ſeruice, only for conſcience ſake, that is, becauſe I thinke it not laweful: for in ſo doing I ſhould offende God
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:13600:90"/>
Almightie greatly, which I muſt not doe for a million of worldes: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you write, that you ſuppoſe me to haue more knowledge, then to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere with ſillie women, it is againſt my conſcience, &amp;c. and aske, vvhat Scripture, authoritie, or reaſon I haue for my refuſing? I thought it good &amp; conuenient to ſhew you briefly ſome arguments &amp; reaſons, which I know not how to anſwere if I ſhould follow your counſaile: But I will not ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie or explane them at large, for ſo I ſhould be long and ouer tedious for you, who (if I be not deceaued) can hardly endure to reade through anie prolixe diſcourſe: but I wil only point as it were at them with my finger, for I know your wits to be ready enough to conceaue the vvhole by a part, or parcell. To begin therefore, I tell you plainely, that the reaſons, why I being a Catholike, and moſt ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing the Catholike Religion to be moſt true, and conſequently all other Sects and religions falſe, and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, will not goe to heare your ſeruice,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:13600:90"/>
or a ſermon of your religion, are theſe which follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In ſo doing, I ſhould furniſh the Campe of the enimies of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church with my viſible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, which may not be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence, for:<note place="margin">Prouer. 14</note> In the multitude of his people is the Kinges dignitie, and in the ſmall number of his folke, the ignominy of the Prince; I leſſen ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the number of Catholikes, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the number of Proteſtantes, at the leaſt in open ſhow.</p>
            <p n="2">2 I ſhould yeeld to an act of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary religion, exacted of me as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of mine, which may not be done without great offence: for although you inculcate, and ingeminate obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and dutifulnes to our Prince, &amp; that it is but an act of obedience: ſure lie I cannot ſee but that it is an act of religion: for albeit the Statute beare this title: <hi>An act to retaine her Maiesties ſubiects in theyr due obedience,</hi> yet is not meere obedience the marke intended
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:13600:91"/>
in the Satute: for the ordinary way to exact obedience is by othes of fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and homage. And why ſhould this law be made for odedience, and none els? or why ſhuld obedience be rather ſhewed in the Church then in other places? or why by ioyning with prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in their ſeruice, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maner of waies? And I pray you, is not obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce included in euery law as well as in this? for it is verie plaine, that euery precept or law beſides obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it ſelfe, intendeth ſome acte of ſome other vertue. And in this law none can be intended but about reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: and ſo in going to your ſeruice I ſhuld make outward profeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your religion, which in my conſcience I iudge to be falſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 I ſhould deny my Faith by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for before the law of going to the Church was made, there was no ſuch bond for <hi>Catholikes</hi> to profeſſe their faith in refuſing the Church, as after there was, although I doe not denie, but that it was vnlawfull euen before the Satute, as being a thing euill in it
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:13600:91"/>
owne nature, to goe formally to their Seruice: but now euery Catholike is bound to profeſſe his faith in refuſing to go to the proteſtants Seruice, when it is exacted of him according to the Satute, which intendeth to draw him from Catholike Religion And wee ſee by experience, that what Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſoeuer goeth to theyr Seruice, be hee neuer ſo zealous in minde in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion, yet is hee of euerie man reckoned in the number of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes, and of all Catholickes vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie diſclaimed. And ſuch a one is in very deed a flatte partaker of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantiſme, and is incorporated <hi>ipſo facto</hi> with the members of the ſame, &amp; vtterly excluded from the participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Miſticall Body of Chriſt our Sauiour. 4 You might by the ſame reaſon vrge me to receiue your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, by which you mooue mee to go to your Seruice: which I hope you will not do, knowing it to be ſo oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to my faith, &amp; religion: for I may ſhewe my obedience to my Princes lawes as wel in the one as in the other.
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:13600:92"/>
And I knowe vvell enough that the Communion is but a peece of bread, and a ſuppe of wine, which are things no leſſe indifferent of themſelues, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my preſence at your ſeruice is. And as I know that your miniſter vvould giue me that bread and wine inſteede of a farre better thing: ſo woulde hee buzze, and ſound in mine eares your ſeruice, I am ſure, in liew of a far more holy thing. And as I little eſteeme your ſeruice, ſo make I ſmall account of your bread and wine: But indeede the true cauſe why I will doe neither the one, nor the other, is becauſe they be both a like acts of religion, vſed in things which I deeme moſte vntrue: yet might obedience excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both in your opinion.</p>
            <p n="5">5 I ſhould <hi>ipſo facto</hi> be Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,<note place="margin">Calet. 2.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 12. ar. 1. &amp; q. 94. ar. 1.</note> and cut off from the Catholike Church of Chriſt: for ſhe excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating generallie all heretikes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth me in the number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe in exteriour court or ſhow, I am an heretike by going to any other ſeruice, then that of the ſaide Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:13600:92"/>
Church, &amp; ſhee not knowing the mind or affection, iudgeth according to the outward ſhow, and ſo reputeth me for an abſolute heretike, although keeping my Faith inuiolable, I be not ſo inwardly, and in very deed. By this meanes I ſhould be vſed as an excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat perſon, altogether cut off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods viſible church, barred from ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſeruice, &amp; ſacraments: for no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Prieſt could lawfullie admitt me to any ſuch, ſo long as I would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that miſerable ſtate.</p>
            <p n="6">6 I ſhould be contrary to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, a fauourer, and a furtherer of Proteſtantes Religion; for I by my preſence encreaſing your number (as I ſaid before) muſt needes ſomewhat augment the credit of your congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and ſo make your ſect to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the more, and encourage others by mine example to help forward the ſame.</p>
            <p n="7">7 I ſhould looſe that peace, vvhich coupleth vs to God, and maketh vs of one hart, &amp; ſoule amongſt our ſelues:<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> and which was ſo much ſought for by
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:13600:93"/>
the penitent lapſed Chriſtians of the Primitiue Church. Their admiſsion, or reconciling againe to the Church after theyr fall was tearmed giuing of peace:<note place="margin">Cyp. lib. 1. Epiſt. 2.</note> for GOD knoweth how little peace, reſt, or quietneſſe of minde a Catholike going to your ſeruice hath. And no meruail, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as his body go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth one way &amp; his mind another, yea he a member rent off from the whole bodie.</p>
            <p n="8">8 I ſhould be adiudged by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church both a Schiſmatike, and an Heretike in ſo doing. A Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matike, becauſe I goe to a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church of God: an Heretike, in that I couple my ſelfe to them who teach hereſie: for being by that deed (as I ſaid before) an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior Heretike, I am conſequently a ſchiſmatike, becauſe that euery here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike is withall a ſchiſmatike, but euery ſchiſmatike is not an heretike: for a ſchiſmatike only is hee, who holding the ſame opinions,<note place="margin">Lib. 20 co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fauſt. c. 3. &amp; con. Creſcon.</note> and vſing the ſame ceremonies of worſhipping God with others, yet only is pleaſed with a ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall congregation.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:13600:93"/>9 I ſhould in ſo doing make a great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie in profeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my faith, which muſt needs be a great ſin: for a lie is as well committed in deed by diſsimulation,<note place="margin">Ambr. ſer. de Abra.</note> as in ſpeech. And my preſence at pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants ſeruice telleth that I am a pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtant, whereas in my hart &amp; conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I am a Catholike. This kinde of lying (as ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi>) ought moſt chieflie to be auoyded, for that it is made in the moſt nobleſt of all morall vertues, I meane Religion.</p>
            <p n="10">10 I ſhould giue great ſcandale, &amp; occaſion of fall to others; for that they ſeeing me doe againſt my conſcience in this, may thinke that I will as eaſlie doe any thing els which I know to be naught, vpon hope of repentance, and ſo by mine example may be mooued to doe the like: for hee who knoweth or thinketh in his conſcience your Seruice to be vnlawfull, and yet will be preſent at it, vvhy will hee not as eaſilie doe anie other thing which hee knoweth to be euill? Beſides, others vvoulde by this myne example, bee Confirmed in Schiſme, and Hereſie,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:13600:94"/>
thinking the ſeruice either to be good and godly indeed, or at the leaſt-wiſe that it may begone vnto without any ſcruple. As thoſe who ſaw others eate Idolothytes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> were confirmed, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to doe the like.</p>
            <p n="11">11 I ſhould endaunger my ſelfe to be infected with that doctrine, which I iudge to be damnable. And I am told that:<note place="margin">Eccl. 13.</note> 
               <hi>he who loueth daunger ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh therein. And if I will not be bitten with a Snake, I muſt not ſleep nigh an hedge: neyther ought I to touch pitch, leaſt I be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed by the ſame.</hi> And if <hi>Dauid</hi> had not aduentured to gaze vpon <hi>Bethſabee</hi> he had not fallen into ſo great liking of her, as to commit ſuch horrible ſinnes as you know. And if no Catholicke would haue heard <hi>Luth.</hi> to haue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he began this new doctrin, there had beene at this day neyther <hi>Lutheran, Zwinglian, Proteſtant, Puritane,</hi> nor any ſuch late ſprung vp fellowes, to trouble and moleſt the Catholicke Church.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 I ſhould diſobey S. <hi>Paule</hi> his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, bidding mee <hi>auoyde an
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:13600:94"/>
Hereticall man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3 2. Tim. 4</note> And farre ſhould I be from the minde of the holy Apoſtle, and Euangeliſt, S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> who durſt not ſo much as ſtay in the bathe to vvaſh in the companie of <hi>Cerinthus</hi> the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike.<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 3 cap. 22</note> What would the ſame Holie Saint haue ſaid thinke you, if hee had bin requeſted by his deare vvorldlie frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, to haue bin preſent at the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſeruice, &amp; ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of <hi>Cirinth.</hi> for the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Lib. 3. c. 30</note> and their ſchollers (as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth <hi>Nicephorus</hi>) vvere ſo warie in this caſe, that they would not ſo much as once reaſon the matter with any of them that endeuoured by their lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges to corrupt the truth. And ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ignatius</hi> boldly affirmeth that,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 6. ad Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phenſes.</note> vvho ſo flieth not from a falſe preacher ſhal be damned into Hell.</p>
            <p n="13">13 I ſhould be partaker of all their wickednes, &amp; conſequently in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of al the puniſhment &amp; miſchiefe which may befal them, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent with them at the deede, wherein principally they offend God: from vvhich thing I am diſcouraged by the terrible death of all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:13600:95"/>
were in company with the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes <hi>Chore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num 16.</note> 
               <hi>Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiron:</hi> which example (as ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>) ought to mooue vs not to aſsiſte, or further Hereticall oblations,<note place="margin">Cyp. Epiſt 76.</note> praiers, ſermons, and errours.</p>
            <p n="14">14 I ſhould contrary to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the learned of all Religions: for the Gentiles thought it not lawfull to enter into the Iewes Synagogues,<note place="margin">Lact lib. 4. &amp; 5. diuin. inſtit. cur. Senec de hiſt. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hom. chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſang Driſl. Euſ. lib. 3. &amp; 4. Aug. li. de vnit. Ecl. &amp; lib. 2. coa. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian. Ioh. Gard. in his Cat. art. 86.</note> or into Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Churches The <hi>Turks</hi> at this day refuſe to doe the ſame, the <hi>Arrians, Donatists,</hi> and ſuch like, would not one goe to anothers conuenticles, nor to the Catholikes ſeruice, nor the Catholikes to any of theirs. The <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptistes</hi> will not goe to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> Churches, nor the <hi>Lutheranes</hi> to the <hi>Trinitaries.</hi> The <hi>Puritanes</hi> vvill hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie be drawen to <hi>Protestantes</hi> ſeruice: neither will the <hi>Proteſtantes</hi> in <hi>Catholike</hi> Countreis come to <hi>Catholike</hi> Seruice. And the <hi>Iewes</hi> will not go to any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice but their own. Thoſe <hi>Protestantes</hi> which in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie conſcience, refuſed to go to <hi>Maſſe.</hi> And therefore in reaſon you ſhoulde
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:13600:95"/>
not mooue me, much leſſe vrge me, to doe the thing, vvhich the learned on your ſide in theyr owne caſe would not doe, becauſe they iudge it vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p n="15">15 I ſhould doe euil to goe to your Seruice becauſe I cannot, but in mine own conſcience iudge it to be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to God, and conſequentlie naught. For to omit to ſpeake how, it is deuiſed by your ſelues, and how your fellovv PVRITANES doe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie condemne it. I knowe your Tranſlations of Holie Scriptures to be falſe &amp; ſhameles, ſo as if my ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſhould tranſlate one of <hi>Tullyes</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles in ſuch corrupt maner, I would ſoundlie breeche him for his labour. Then your Miniſters are no Prieſtes, but meere Lay-men, &amp; conſequently haue no authoritie to deale in ſuch things. Beſides you haue in your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice diuerſe falſe and blaſphemous things, &amp; put them to the people for Scripture; as in a <hi>Geneua Pſal</hi> you pray to be defended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Pope, Turke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, &amp;c.</hi> And to ſpeake what I thinke,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:13600:96"/>
you haue left out all good thinges, &amp; haue choſen to your ſelues iuſte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Catholike ſeruice, although the people were made to beleeue that it was the old Seruice put into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</p>
            <p n="16">16 I ſhoulde goe to that Seruice which neuer was heard of in the world before theſe dayes: nor yet is in anie place els in all the world, but onelie there in England.</p>
            <p n="17">17 I ſhoulde goe to that Seruice, which you amongſt your ſelues can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or decree to continue. And it had by all likelihoode beene chaunged againe before this day, if the grauer ſorte had not made ſome ſtay, for feare of incurring the note of inconſtancy: for how many bils I pray you, haue there bin put vp in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments about the chaunging of your Seruice? Agree therefore amongeſt your ſelues firſt what ſeruice you will haue to continue, and then I will aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere you reaſonablie to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund.</p>
            <p n="18">18 In ſo doing my ſoule ſhould goe
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:13600:96"/>
one way, and my body another; which ought not to be: for if they ſhould goe two waies in this worlde, they could not be ioyned togeather after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection in the next life, but the one ſhould goe to heauen, &amp; the other to hell; which cannot be: for if the bodie ſerue not God together with the ſoule in this life, why ſhould it enioy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the next? And if it be with Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes at their Seruice in this worlde, why ſhould it not be where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants be in the next?</p>
            <p n="19">19 I ſhould loofe all the benefit of Catholike religion, &amp; ſo either leaue off all conſcience, or els liue in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall torment of mind; and if I ſhould die in that ſtate, I ſhould be vtterlie caſt away for euer. Beſides I ſhoulde looſe the merite of all the good works that I euer did in all my life; becauſe I giue ouer working before euening, &amp; ſo looſe my pennie, &amp; wages which otherwiſe would be truely paide mee.<note place="margin">Mat. 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 If I ſhould ſo doe, either to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie you, &amp; other of my friends, or by commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of any power vnder
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:13600:97"/>
her Maieſtie: neyther you, nor they, could take it well, or account of mee, better then of a trayterous caitiue, for that you muſt needs think that I, who will violate my faith to God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in doing contrarie to my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, &amp; iudgment for any worldly reſpect, will eaſily breake my faith &amp; promiſe with man, according to the iudgment of <hi>Constantius</hi> the Emperour:<note place="margin">Euſ. de vit. canſtant. l. 1. cap. 11.</note> for how can he be true vnto man, that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted of periurie to God? verily ſuch muſt needs be deemed of the wiſe, to be flatterers, turne-coates, and great hypocrits.</p>
            <p n="21">21 And now to come to the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, which you ſay women, &amp; ſuch ſillie ſoules are accuſtomed to make; I ſhould do contrary to my conſcience: which thing in no caſe is lawfull to be done. Yea if your ſeruice were good, &amp; godly indeed, &amp; the very true Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, yet ſo long as I thinke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of it, I may in no caſe yeeld to go to it: becauſe an erroneous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bindeth a man to follow it, &amp; neuer to doe any thing againſt it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:13600:97"/>
to iudgement of all learned men, of what ſect, or religion ſoeuer they be. And therefore you may not requeſt me, much-leſſe vrge me to go to your ſeruice, before I be perſwaded in my conſcience that it is lawful ſo to doe. Greatly therfore doe you offend God there in <hi>England,</hi> in forcing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to goe to the Church, contrary to their conſciences, and in impriſoning thoſe, who refuſe ſo to do: for no man is able to maiſter his own conſcience, &amp; knowledge, and to doe againſt it he ought not, &amp; therefore it is not in his power or will, to goe to your Seruice without offence.</p>
            <p n="22">22 I ſhould do contrary to the Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons &amp; cuſtome of the <hi>Catholik church,</hi> and againſt the examples of all Holie Saints, &amp; learned Fathers. Contrarie to the 63. Canon of the Apoſtles, and againſt <hi>Concil. Carth.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 71. <hi>&amp;</hi> 72. <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Antioch. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>Con. Laodicen. c.</hi> 9. 32. 33. 37. <hi>Con. Mag. Later. cap.</hi> 70. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diuers other <hi>Councels,</hi> as alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the late <hi>Councell of Trent,</hi> where the matter was put (<hi>Engliſh Catholikes</hi>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:13600:98"/>
making ſuite that it might be couert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcuſſed, &amp; decided) to 12. lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Fathers; whoſe iudgement in this matter is yet extant, and it had bin ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous to haue in any publike Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there condemned the ſame, which by ſo many <hi>Councels</hi> before that was plainly forbidden. Againſt the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Saints, &amp; learned Fathers, as of <hi>S. I. Euang.</hi> which I recited before, of <hi>S. Polycarpe,</hi> of <hi>S. Denis Biſhop of Alexandria,</hi> of <hi>S. Anth,</hi> of <hi>Origen,</hi> of <hi>Beniolus, S. Amb. S. Athan. S. Chriſoſt.</hi> and of many moe.</p>
            <p n="23">23 I ſhould in ſo doing ſhew my ſelf a <hi>Neuter,</hi> that is, ſuch a one as is not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to either religion, &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of no religion,<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.</note> but an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> or nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hote nor cold, but luke warme, &amp; therfore to be ſpued out of the mouth of God:<note place="margin">3. Reg. 18.</note> for hee who haulteth on both ſides, is on neither ſide, but a traitour to bothe. And from the one, and the ſame fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain there runneth not ſweet &amp; ſower water:<note place="margin">Iacob. 3.</note> neyther can any man ſerue two contrary maſters: as he can not plow with an Oxe &amp; an Aſſe,<note place="margin">Mat 6. Deut. 22.</note> nor weare garments of linnin &amp; wolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:13600:98"/>
ſow his field with two maner of ſeeds.</p>
            <p n="24">24 I ſhould in ſo doing be (as is ſaid before) one of your congregation, and yet I ſhould be but the verie excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or chippings of your Church: for receauing no life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in the corps of <hi>Proteſtantiſme</hi> I ſhould ſerue for no neceſſarie vſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I could not be ther, but for ſome worldly reſpect, &amp; ſo in body only, &amp; by that meanes but as the haires of a mans body, or nailes, or euill humors: which althogh they be within the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet are they not animated by the ſoul, but void of ſenſe, &amp; loſt without paine, &amp; by nature not fit to be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: for fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſpirit I hope I ſhould ſucke no zeale of that ſect, &amp; from the ſoule of the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> I could receaue no life, becauſe I cutt my ſelfe off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, by yeelding to your ſeruice, and ſo I ſhould remaine void of ſenſe, life, and ſoule, and ſhould be nothing but <hi>Caluins</hi> excrements.</p>
            <p n="25">25 I ſhould ſhewe my ſelfe a colde Catholike, &amp; indeed to haue no zeale at all, for that deeming you to bee
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:13600:99"/>
Gods enemies, yet I can finde in my hart not only to be in companye with you in ciuill affaires, but alſo in your ſeruice, far from the ſpirit of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> who hated the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch, and was euen eaten with the zeale of Gods Church, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loued the beutye thereof. Yea, I ſhoulde doe quite contrary, for when I ſee a theefe, I ſhould run with him, &amp; take part with the adulterers. And to conclude with anſwering your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, why I will not as well goe to your ſeruice, as eate fleſhe vpon a fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, when vrgent occaſions driue me thereunto: I ſay, that Religion being a vertue which giueth honour &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to God, doth ſometimes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand other vertues, &amp; directeth their actions to Gods honor.<note place="margin">Theod. 22. q. 85. art. 3</note> As faſting is a vertue that ſubdueth mans body, and may be commaunded by religion to ſerue God withall. Other actes there are, which only belong to religion, &amp; not to other vertues, which haue no other praiſe, but that they are done for the reuerence of God: of vvhich
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:13600:99"/>
ſort are ſacrifies, kneeling, knocking on the breſt, &amp; ſuch like. And of this ſort is the ceremonie of going to ſuch a place more then to another. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it is that one may eate fleſh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a friday, or other faſting in diuers caſes, and yet in no caſe goe to ſeruice with thoſe who are of a falſe religion: for to abſtaine vpon certaine dayes, is not a proper, or immediate act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but commaunded by religion, being indeed an act of temperance, &amp; ſo intended by holy Church, although it may be vſed to honor God with all. And becauſe none vſe to faſt on ſuch daies but <hi>Catholikes,</hi> it doth oftentimes betoken a <hi>Catholike,</hi> &amp; diſtinguiſheth him from <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> yet becauſe the immediate end of the law is tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, &amp; the act of eating of fleſh or of other forbidden meats, hath other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ends beſides religion, therefore it doth not neceſſarily containe anie ſignification of religion: but the act of going to the Church doth of it own nature, &amp; by common acceptation of all betoken deuotion and religion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:13600:100"/>Thus haue I brieflie yeelded you ſome reaſons and authorities, why I may not ſatiſfie your requeſt, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcende to your deſires in going to your ſeruice. I coulde haue yeelded many moe, but I thought theſe might ſuffice you, and cauſe you to ſurceaſe from your worldly, &amp; carnall perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: for hereafter I meane not to aunſwere you any more ſuch letters, but only to ſay vnto you, goe behinde me <hi>Satans</hi> for you are ſcandales to me. And ſo deſiring our Parents bleſsing with humble commendations to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and harty to you, and to all the reſte of our kinſfolkes and friendes, I leaue you all to our Lord and Sauiour, who ſend vs his grace in this world, and his glory in the next. <hi>From my Chamber at Palempyne this</hi> 18. <hi>of Februarie.</hi> 1600.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13600:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> A bryef &amp; ſhort declaracyon made, wherbye e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> chryſten man maye knowe, what is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Of what partes a ſacraments conſyſteth and is made, for what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſacramentes were inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and what is the pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypall effect of ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, &amp; finally of the abuſe of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of chryſten body and bloud.</p>
            <p>Imprinted At London by Robert Stoughton Dwellynge wythin Ludgate. at the ſygne of the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
